<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Watermark</title>
                <author>Joseph Brodsky</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1"><date>May 2025</date></edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Annotations by</resp>
                    <name>Artem Romashov</name>
                    <name>Arina Gracheva</name>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Digital edition of Joseph Brodsky's essay "Watermark"</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>https://shakko.wordpress.com/2014/07/04/joseph-brodsky-watermark/</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This file is part of a project dedicated to the Russian-American poet Joseph Brodsky and Venice. Completed as part of a final project for course "Information Science and Cultural Heritage", Digital Humanities and Digital Knowledge, University of Bologna.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><p>In this text, in addition to the basic elements (chapters, paragraphs), locations mentioned in the essay, expressions in foreign languages, and quotes from other works are also marked.</p></interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <div type="dedication">
                <p>To Robert Morgan</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
                <p>Many moons ago the dollar was 870 lire and I was thirty-two. The globe, too, was lighter by two billion souls, and the bar at 
                    the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164596">stazione</placeName> where I'd arrived on that cold December night was empty. I was standing there waiting for the only person I knew in 
                    that city to meet me. She was quite late.</p>
                <p>Every traveler knows this fix: this mixture of fatigue and apprehension. It's the time of staring down clock faces and 
                    timetables, of scrutinizing varicose marble under your feet, ofinhaling ammonia and that dull smell elicitedon cold winter nights by 
                    locomotives' cast iron. I did all this.</p>
                <p>Save for the yawning bartender and immobile Buddha-like <foreign xml:lang="la">matrona</foreign> at the cash register, there was no one in sight. However, we were of no use 
                    to each other: my sole currency in their language, the term "espresso," was already spent; I'd used it twice. I'd also bought from them 
                    my first pack ever of what in years to come was to stand for "<foreign xml:lang="it">Merde Statale</foreign>", "<foreign xml:lang="it">Movimento Sociale</foreign>", and "<foreign xml:lang="it">Morte Sicura</foreign>": my first pack of MS. 
                    So I lifted my bags and stepped outside.</p>
                <p>In the unlikely event that someone's eye followed my white London Fog and dark brown Borsalino, they should have cut a familiar silhouette. 
                    The night itself, to be sure, would have had no difficulty absorbing it. Mimicry, I believe, is high on the list of every traveler, and 
                    the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175395">Italy</placeName> I had in mind at the moment was a fusion of black-and-white movies of the fifties and the equally monochrome medium of my metier.
                    Winter thus was my season; theonly thing I lacked, I thought, to look like a local rake or <foreign xml:lang="it">carbonaro</foreign> was a scarf. Other than that, I felt 
                    inconspicuous and fit to merge into the background or fill the frame of a low-budget whodunit or, more likely, melodrama.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="2">
                <p>It was a windy night, and before my retina registered anything, I was smitten by a feeling of utter happiness: my nostrils were hit by what 
                    to me has always been its synonym, the smell of freezing seaweed. For some people, it's freshly cut grass or hay; for others, Christmas scents 
                    of conifer needles and tangerines. For me, it's freezing seaweed partly because of onomatopoeic aspects of the very conjunction (in Russian, 
                    seaweed is a wonderful <foreign xml:lang="ru">vodorosli</foreign>), partly due to a slight incongruity and a hidden underwater drania in this notion. One recognizes oneself in 
                    certain elements; by the time I was taking this smell in on the steps of the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164596">stazione</placeName>, hiddendramas and incongruities long since had become my 
                    forte.</p>
                <p>No doubt the attraction toward that smell should have been attributed to a childhood spent by the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2633321">Baltic</placeName>,
                    the home of that meandering siren from the Montale poem. And yet I had my doubts about this attribution. For one thing, that childhood wasn't all that happy (a childhood seldom is, 
                    being, rather, a school of self-disgust and insecurity); and as for the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2633321">Baltic</placeName>, you had indeed to be an eel to escape my part of it. At any 
                    rate, as a subject for nostalgia this childhood hardly qualified. The source of that attraction, I'd always felt, lay elsewhere, beyond the 
                    confines of biography, beyond one's genetic makeup somewhere in one's hypothalamus, which stores our chordate ancestors' impressions of their 
                    native realm of for example the very ichthus that caused this civilization. Whether that ichthus was a happy one is another matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="3">
                <p>A smell is, after all, a violation ofoxygen balance, an invasion into it of other elements methane? carbon? sulphur? nitrogen? Depending on 
                    that invasion's intensity, you get a scent, a smell, a stench. It is a molecular affair, and happiness, I suppose, is the moment of spotting 
                    the elements of your own composition being free. There were quite a number of them out there, in a state of total freedom, and I felt I'd 
                    stepped into my own self-portrait in the cold air.</p>
                <p>The backdrop was all in dark silhouettes of church cupolas and rooftops; a bridge arching over a body of water's black curve, both ends of 
                    which were clipped off by infinity. At night, infinity in foreign realms arrives with the last lamppost, and here it was twenty meters away. 
                    It was very quiet. A few dimly lit boats now and then prowled about, disturbing with their propellers the reflection of a large neon Cinzano 
                    trying to settle on the black oilcloth ofthe water's surface. Long before it succeeded, the silence would be restored.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4">
                <p>It all felt like arriving in the provinces, in some unknown, insignificant spot possibly one's own birthplace after years of absence. In no 
                    small degree did this sensation owe to my own anonymity, to the incongruity of a lone figure on the steps of the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164596">stazione</placeName>: an easy target for 
                    oblivion. Also, it was a winter night. And I remembered the opening line of one of Uniberto Saba's poems that I'd translated long before, in a 
                    previous incarnation, into Russian: <quote>"In the depths ofthe wild <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3183462">Adriatic</placeName> . . . "</quote> In the depths, I thought, in the boondocks, in a lost corner of 
                    the wild <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3183462">Adriatic</placeName> . . . Had I simply turned around, I'd have seen the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164596">stazione</placeName> in all its rectangular splendor of neon and urbanity, seen block 
                    letters saying <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">VENEZIA</placeName>. Yet I didn't. The sky was full of winter stars, the way it often is in theprovinces. At any point, it seemed, a dog 
                    could bark in the distance, or else you might hear a rooster. With niy eyes shut I beheld a tuft of freezing seaweed splayed against a wet, 
                    perhaps ice-glazed rock somewhere in the universe, oblivious to its location. I was that rock, and niy left palm was that splayed tuft of 
                    seaweed. Presently ?. large, flat boat, something of a cross between a sardine can and a sandwich, emerged out of nowhere and with a thud 
                    nudged the sfaziane's landing. A handful of people pushed ashore and raced past me up the stairs into the terminal. Then I saw the only 
                    person I knew in that city; the sight was fabulous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5">
                <p>I had seen it for the first time several years before, in that same previous incarnation: in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2017370">Russia</placeName>. The sight had come there in the guise 
                    ofa Slavicist, a Mayakovsky scholar, to be precise. That nearly disqualifiedthe sight as a subject of interest in the eyes of the coterie 
                    to which i belonged. That it didn't was the measure of her visual properties. Five foot ten, fine-boned, long-legged, narrow-faced, with 
                    chestnut hair and hazel, almond- shaped eyes, with passable Russian on those wonderfully shaped lips and a blinding smile on the same, 
                    superbly dressed in paper-light suede and matching silks, redolent of mesmerizing, unknown to us, perfume, the sight was easily the most 
                    elegant female ever to set a mind-boggling foot in our midst. She was the kind that keeps married men's dreams wet. Besides, she was a Veneziana.</p>
                <p>So we gave short shrift to her membership in the Italian CP and her attendant sentiment toward our avant-garde simpletons of the thirties, 
                    attributing both to Western frivolity. Had she been even an avowed Fascist, i think we would have lusted after her no less. She was positively 
                    stunning, and when subsequently she'd fallen for the worst possible dimwit on the periphery of our circle, some highly paiddolt of Armenian 
                    extraction, the common response was amazement and anger rather than jealousy or manly regret. Of course, come to think of it, one shouldn't get 
                    angry over a piece of fine lace soiled by some strong ethnic juices. Yet \ve did. For it was more than a letdown: it was a betrayal of the fabric.</p>
                <p>In those days we associated style with substance, beauty with intelligence. After all, we were a bookish crowd, and at a certain age, if you 
                    believe in literature, you think everyone shares or should share your conviction and taste. So if one looks elegant, one is one of us. 
                    Innocent of the world outside, of the West in particular, we didn't know yet that style could be purchased wholesale, that beauty could be just 
                    a commodity. So we regarded the sight as the physical extension and embodiment of our ideals and principles, and what she wore, transparent 
                    things included, belonged to civilization.</p>
                <p>So strong was that association, and so pretty was the sight, that even now, years later, belonging to a different age and, as it were, to a 
                    different country, I began to slip unwittingly into the old mode. The first thing I asked her as I stood pressed to her nutria coat on the deck 
                    of the overcrowded vaporetto was her opinion of Montale's Motets, recently published. The familiar flash of her pearls, thirty-two strong, 
                    echoed by the sparkle on the rim of her hazel pupil and promoted to the scattered silver of the Milky Way overhead, was all I got in response, 
                    but that was a lot. To ask, in the heart of civilization, about its latest was perhaps a tautology. Perhaps I was simply being impolite, as the 
                    author wasn't a local.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="6">
                <p>The boat's slow progress through the night was like the passage of a coherent thought through the subconscious. On both sides, knee-deep 
                    in pitch-black water, stood the enormous carved chests of dark palazzi filled with unfathomable treasures most likely gold, judging from 
                    the low-intensity yellow electric glow emerging now and then from cracks in the shutters. The overall feeling was mythological, cyclopic, to be 
                    precise: I'd entered that infinity I beheld on the steps of the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164596">stazione</placeName> and now was moving among its inhabitants, along the bevy of dormant 
                    cyclopses reclining in black water, now and then raising and lowering an eyelid.</p>
                <p>The nutria-clad sight next to me began explaining in a somewhat hushed voice that she was taking me to my hotel, where she had reserved a room, 
                    that perhaps we'd meet tomorrow or the day after, that she'd like to introduce me to her husband and her sister. I liked the hush in her voice, 
                    though it fit the night more than the message, and replied in the same conspiratorial tones that it's always a pleasure to meet potential 
                    relatives. That was a bit strong for the moment, but she laughed, in the same muffled way, putting a hand in abrown leather glove to her lips. 
                    The passengers around us, mostly dark-haired, whose number was responsible for our proximity, were immobile and equally subdued in their 
                    occasional remarks to one another, as though the content of their exchanges was also of an intimate nature. Then the sky was momentarily 
                    obscured by the huge marble parenthesis of a bridge, and suddenly everything was flooded with light. "<placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/7302944/">Rialto</placeName>," she said in her normal voice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7">
                <p>There is something primordial about traveling on water, even for short distances. You are informed that you are not supposed to be there not so 
                    much by your eyes, ears, nose, palate, or palm as by your feet, which feel odd acting as an organ of sense. Water unsettles the principle of 
                    horizontality, especially at night, when its surface resembles pavement. No matter how solid its substitute the deck under your feet, on water 
                    you are somewhat more alert than ashore, your faculties are more poised. On water, for instance, you never get absentminded the way you do in 
                    the street: your legs keep you and your wits in constant check, as if you were some kind of compass. Well, perhaps what sharpens your wits 
                    while traveling on water is indeed a distant, roundabout echo of the good old chor- dates. At any rate, your sense of the other on water gets 
                    keener, as though heightened by a common as well as a mutual danger. The loss of direction is a psychological category as much as it is a 
                    navigational one. Be that as it may, for the next ten minutes, although we were moving in the same direction, I saw the arrow of the only 
                    person I knew in that city and mine diverge by at least 45 degrees. Most likely because this part of the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175933">Canal Grande</placeName> was better lit.</p>
                <p>We disembarked at the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/7910507">Accademia</placeName> landing, prey to firm topography and the correspondingmoral code. After a short meander through narrow 
                    lanes, I was deposited in the lobby of a somewhat cloistered <foreign xml:lang="it">pensione</foreign>, kissed on the cheek more in the capacity of the Minotaur, I felt, 
                    than the valiant hero and wished good night. Then my Ariadne vanished, leaving behind a fragrant thread of her expensive (was it Shalimar?) 
                    perfume, which quickly dissipated in the musty atmosphere of a <foreign xml:lang="it">pensione</foreign> otherwise suffused with the faint but ubiquitous odor ofpee. 
                    I stared for a while at the furniture. Then I hit the sack.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8">
                <p>That's how I found myself for the first time in this city. As it turned out, there was nothing particularly auspicious or ominous about this 
                    arrival of mine. If that night portended anything at all, it was that I'd never possess this city; but then I never had any such aspiration. 
                    As a beginning, I think this episodewill do, although as far as the-only-person-I-knew-in-this-city was concerned, it rather marked the end 
                    of our acquaintance. I saw her two or three times subsequently during that stay in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName>; and indeed I was introduced to her sister and to her 
                    husband. The former turned out to be a lovely woman: as tall and slender as my Ariadne and perhaps even brighter, but more melancholy and, 
                    for all I could tell, even more married. The latter, whose appearance completely escapes my memory for reasons of redundancy, was a scumbag 
                    of an architect, of that ghastly postwar persuasion that has done more harm to the European skyline than any Luftwaffe. In 
                    <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName>, he defiled a couple ofwonderful <foreign xml:lang="it">campi</foreign> with his edifices, one of which was naturally a bank,
                    since this sort of human animal loves a bank with absolutely narcissistic fervor, with the longing of an effect for its cause. For that "structure" (as they called it in those days) alone, I thought, he 
                    should be cuckolded. Butsince, like his wife, he, too, seemed to be a member of the CP, the job, I concluded, was best left to a comrade.</p>
                <p>Fastidiousness was one part of it; the other part was that when, somewhat later, I called the-only-person-I-knew-in-that-city from the depths 
                    of my labyrinth one blue evening, the architect, perhaps sensing in my broken Italian something untoward, cut the thread. So now it really 
                    was up to our red Armenian brethren.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9">
                <p>Subsequently, I was told, she divorced the man and married a U.S. Air Force pilot, who turned out to be the nephew of the mayor of a small 
                    town in the great <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/5001836">state ofMichigan</placeName>, where I once dwelt. Small world, and the longer you live, no man or woman makes it larger. So were I 
                    looking for consolation, I could derive it from the thought that we now are both treading the same ground ofa different continent. This sounds, 
                    ofcourse, like Statius talking to Virgil, but then it's only proper for the likes of me to regard <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/6252001">America</placeName> as a kind ofPurgatorio - not to mention
                    Dante himself suggesting as much. The only difference is that her heaven is far better settled than mine. Hence my forays into my version of 
                    Paradise, which she inaugurated so graciously. At any rate, for the last seventeen years I've been returning to this city, or recurring in it, 
                    with the frequency of a bad dream.</p>
                <p>With two or three exceptions, due to heart attacks and related emergencies, niine or someone else's, every Christmas or shortly before I'd emerge 
                    from a train/plane/boat/bus and drag my bags heavy with books and typewriters to the threshold of this or that hotel, of this or that apartment. 
                    The latter would normally be courtesy of the one or two friends I'd managed to develop here in the wake ofthe sight's dimming. Later, I'll try to 
                    account for my timing (though such a project is tautological to the point of reversal). For the moment, I'd like to assert that, Northerner though 
                    I am, my notion of Eden hinges on neither weather nor temperature. For that matter, I'd just as soon discard its dwellers, and eternity as well. At 
                    the risk of being charged with depravity, I confess that this notion is purely visual, has more to do with Claude than the creed, and exists only in 
                    approximations. As these go, this city is the closest. Since I'm not entitled to make a true comparison, I can permit myself to be restrictive.</p>
                <p>I say this here and now to save the reader disillusionment. I am not a moral man (though I try to keep my conscience in balance) or a sage; I am 
                    neither an aesthete nor a philosopher. I am but a nervous man, by circumstance and by my own deeds; but I am observant. As my beloved Akutagawa 
                    Ryunosuke once said, I have no principles; all I've got is nerves. What follows, therefore, has to do with the eye rather than with convictions, 
                    including those as to how to run a narrative. One's eye precedes one's pen, and I resolve not to let my pen lie about its position. Having risked 
                    the charge of depravity, I won't wince at that of superficiality either. Surfaces which is what the eye registers first are often more telling than 
                    their contents, which are provisional by definition, except, of course, in the afterlife. Scanning this city's face for seventeen winters, I should 
                    by now be capable of pulling a credible Poussin- like job: of painting this place's likeness, if not at four seasons, then at four times of day.</p>
                <p>That's niy ambition. If I get sidetracked, it is because being sidetracked is literally a matter of course here and echoes water. What lies 
                    ahead, in other words, may amount not to a story but to the flow of muddy water "at the wrong time of year." At times it looks blue, at times gray 
                    or brown; invariably it is cold and not potable. The reason I am engaged in straining it is that it contains reflections, among them my own.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="10">
                <p>Inanimate by nature, hotel room mirrors are even further dulled by having seen so many. What they return to you is not your identity but your 
                    anonymity, especially in this city. For here yourself is the last thing you care to see. On my first sojourns I often felt surprised, catching my 
                    own frame, dressed or naked, in the open wardrobe; after a while I began to wonder about this place's edenic or afterlife-like effects upon one's 
                    self- awareness. Somewhere along the line, I even developed a theory of excessive redundancy , of the mirror absorbing the body absorbing the city. 
                    The net result is, obviously, mutual negation. A reflection cannot possibly care for a reflection. The city is narcissistic enough to turn your 
                    mind into an amalgam, unburdening it ofits depths. With their similar effect on your purse, hotels and pensioties therefore feel very congenial. 
                    After a two-week stay even at offseason rates you become both broke and selfless, like a Buddhist monk. At a certain age and in a certain line of 
                    work, selflessness is welcome, not to say imperative.</p>
                <p>Nowadays all of this is, of course, out of the question, since the clever devils shut down two-thirds of the small places in winter; the 
                    remaining third keep year round those summer rates that make you wince. Ifyou're lucky, you may find an apartment, which, naturally, comes with 
                    the owner's personal taste in paintings, chairs, curtains, with a vague sense of illegality to your face in his bathroom mirror  - in short, with 
                    precisely what you wanted to shed: yourself. Still, winter is an abstract season: it is low on colors, even in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175395">Italy</placeName>, and big on the imperatives 
                    of cold and brief daylight. These things train your eye on the outside with an intensity greater than that ofthe electric bulb availing you of your 
                    own features in the evening. If this season doesn't necessarily quell your nerves, it still subordinates them to your instincts; beauty at low 
                    temperatures is beauty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="11">
                <p>Anyhow, I would never come here in summer, not even at gunpoint. I take heat very poorly; the unmitigated emissions of hydrocarbons and armpits 
                    still worse. The shorts-clad herds, especially those neighing in German, also get on my nerves, because ofthe inferiority oftheir anyone's anatomy 
                    against that of the columns, pilasters, and statues; because of what their mobility and all that fuels it projects versus marble stasis. I guess I 
                    ani one of those who prefer choice to flux, and stone is always a choice. No matter how well endowed, in this city one's body, in my view, should 
                    be obscured by cloth, if only because it moves. Clothes are perhaps our only approximation of the choice made by marble.</p>
                <p>This is, I suppose, an extreme view, but I ani a Northerner. In the abstract season life seems more real than at any other, even in the 
                    <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3183462">Adriatic</placeName>, because in winter everything is harder, niore stark. Or else take this as propaganda for Venetian boutiques, which do extremely brisk 
                    business in low temperatures. In part, of course, this is so because in winter one needs more clothes just to stay warm, not to mention the 
                    atavistic urge to shed one's pelt. Yet no traveler comes here without a spare sweater, jacket, skirt, shirt, slacks, or blouse, since <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName> is the 
                    sort of city where both the stranger and the native know in advance that one will be on display.</p>
                <p>No, bipeds go ape about shopping and dressing up in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName> for reasons not exactly practical; they do so because the city, as it were, 
                    challenges them. We all harbor all sorts of misgivings about the flaws in our appearance, anatomy, about the imperfection of our very features. 
                    What one sees in this city at every step, turn, perspective, and dead end worsens one's complexes and insecurities. That's why one  -  a woman 
                    especially, but a man also  -  hits the stores as soon as one arrives here, and with a vengeance. The surrounding beauty issuch that one instantly 
                    conceives of an incoherent animal desire to match it, to be on a par. This has nothing to do with vanity or with the natural surplus of mirrors 
                    here, the main one being the very water. It is simply that the city offers bipeds a notion of visual superiority absent in their natural lairs, 
                    in their habitual surroundings. That's why furs fly here, as do suede, silk, linen, wool, and every other kind of fabric. Upon returning home, 
                    folks stare in wonderment at what they've acquired, knowing full well that there is no place in their native realm to flaunt these acquisitions 
                    without scandalizing the natives. You must keep those things fading and withering in your wardrobe, or else give them to your younger relations. 
                    Or else, there are friends. I, for one, remember buying several items hereon credit, obviouslythat I had no stomach or nerve to utilize later. 
                    Among them were two raincoats, one mustard green and the other a gentle shade ofkhaki. Later they were to grace the shouldersof the world's best 
                    ballet dancer and the best poet of the language I write this indistinct though both these gentlemen are from me in size and age. It's the local 
                    vistas and perspectives that do it, for in this city a man is more a silhouette than his unique features, and a silhouette can be improved. It's 
                    also the marble lace, inlays, capitals, cornices, reliefs, and moldings, inhabited and uninhabited niches, saints, ain'ts, maidens, angels, 
                    cherubs, caryatids, pediments, balconies with their ample kicked-up calves, and windows themselves, Gothic or Moorish, that turn you vain. For this 
                    is the city of the eye; your other faculties play a faint second fiddle. The way the hues and rhythms of the local fa\ades try to smooth the waves' 
                    ever-changing colors and patterns alone may send you to grab a fancy scarf, tie, or whatnot; it glues even an inveterate bachelor to a window 
                    flooded with its motley flaunted dresses, not to mention patent-leather shoes and suede boots scattered like all sorts ofboatsupon the <foreign xml:lang="it">laguna</foreign>. 
                    Somehow your eye suspects that all these things are cut from the same cloth as the vistas outside and ignores the evidence of labels. And in the 
                    final analysis, the eye is not so wrong, if only because the common purpose of everything here is to be seen. In an analysis even more final, this 
                    city is a real triumph of the chordate, because the eye, our only raw, fishlike internal organ, indeed swims here: it darts, flaps, oscillates, 
                    dives, rolls up. Its exposed jelly dwells with atavistic joy on reflected palazzi, spiky heels, gondolas, etc., recognizing in the agency that 
                    brought them to the existential surface none other than itself.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="12">
                <p>In winter you wake up in this city, especially on Sundays , to the chiming ofits innumerable bells, as though behind your gauze curtains a 
                    gigantic china teaset were vibrating on a silver tray in the pearl-gray sky. You fling the window open and the room isinstantly flooded with 
                    this outer, peal-laden haze, which is part damp oxygen, part coffee and prayers. No matter what sort of pills, and how many, you've got to 
                    swallow this morning, you feel it's not over for you yet. No matter, by the same token, how autonomous you are, how niuch you've been betrayed, 
                    how thorough and dispiriting is your self- knowledge, you assume there is still hope for you, or at least a future. (Hope, said Francis Bacon, 
                    is a good breakfast but a bad supper.) This optimism derives from the haze, from the prayer part of it, especially if it is time for breakfast. 
                    On days like this, the city indeed acquires a porcelain aspect, what with all its zinc-covered cupolas resembling teapots or upturned cups, and 
                    the tilted profile ofcanipaniles clinking like abandoned spoons and melting in the sky. Not to mention the seagulls and pigeons, now sharpening 
                    into focus, now melting into air. I should say that, good though this place is for honeymoons, I've often thought it should be tried for 
                    divorces alsoboth in progress and already accomplished. There is no better backdrop for rapture to fade into; whether right or wrong, no 
                    egoist can star for long in this porcelain setting by crystal water, for it steals the show. I am aware, of course, ofthe disastrous 
                    consequence the above suggestions may have for hotel rates here, even in winter. Still, people love their melodrama more than architecture, 
                    and I don't feel threatened. It is surprising that beauty is valued less than psychology, but so long as such is the case, I'll be able to 
                    afford this citywhich means till the end ofmy days, and which ushers in the generous notion of the future.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="13">
                <p>One is what one looks at - well, at least partially. The medieval
                belief that a pregnant woman wishing her child to be beautiful must look
                at beautiful objects is not so naìve given the quality of dreams
                one dreams in this city. Nights here are low on nightmares - judging of
                course by literary sources (especially since nightmares are such
                sources' main fare). Wherever he goes, a sick man, for example - a
                cardiac cripple particularly - is bound to wake up now and then at three
                o'clock in the morning in a state of sheer terror, thinking he's going.
                Yet nothing of the sort, I must report, ever happened to me here; though
                as I write this, I keep my fingers and toes crossed.</p>
                    <p>There are better ways, no doubt, to manipulate dreams, and no doubt
                a good case can be made for it being best done gastronomically. Yet by
                Italian standards, the local diet is not exceptional enough to account
                for this city's concentration of indeed dreamlike beauty in its
                façades alone. For in dreams, as the poet said, begin
                responsibilities. In any case, some of the blueprints - an apt term in
                this city! - certainly sprang from that source, as there is nothing else
                one can trace them to in reality.</p>
                    <p>Should a poet mean to say simply, "In bed," that would hold, too.
                Architecture is surely the least carnal of Muses, since the rectangular
                principle of a building, of its façade in particular,
                militates - and often sharply so - against your analyst's interpretation
                of its cloud- or wave-like - rather than feminine! - cornices, loggias,
                and whatnot. A blueprint, in short, is always more lucid than its
                analysis. Yet many a <foreign xml:lang="it">frontone</foreign> here reminds you precisely of a
                headboard looming above its habitually unmade bed, be it morning or
                evening. They are far more absorbing, these headboards, than those beds'
                possible contents, than the anatomy of your beloved, whose only
                advantage here could be agility or warmth.</p>
                    <p>If there is anything erotic to those blueprints' marble
                consequences, it is the sensation caused by the eye trained on any of
                them - the sensation similar to that of the fingertips touching for the
                first time your beloved's breast or, better yet, shoulder. It is the
                telescopic sensation of coming in contact with the cellular infinity of
                another body's existence - a sensation known as tenderness and
                proportionate perhaps only to the number of cells that body contains.
                (Everyone would understand this, save Freudians, or Muslims believing in
                the veil. But then again, that may explain why among Muslims there are
                so many astronomers. Besides, the veil is a great social planning
                device, since it ensures every female a man regardless of her
                appearance. Worst come to worst, it guarantees that the first-night
                shock is at least mutual. Still, for all the Oriental motifs in Venetian
                architecture, Muslims in this city are the most infrequent visitors.) In
                any case, whichever comes first - reality or dream - one's notion of
                afterlife in this city appears to be well taken care of by its clearly
                paradisaical visual texture. Sickness alone, no matter how grave it may
                be, won't avail you here of an infernal vision. You'd need an
                extraordinary neurosis, or a comparable accumulation of sins, or both,
                to fall prey to nightmares on these premises.</p>
                    <p>That's possible, of course, but not too frequent. For the mild cases
                of either, a sojourn here is the best therapy, and that's what tourism,
                locally, is all about. One sleeps tight in this city, since one's feet
                get too tired quelling a worked-up psyche or guilty conscience alike.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="14">
                <p>Perhaps the best proof of the Almighty's existence is that we never
                know when we are to die. In other words, had life been a solely human
                affair, one would be issued at birth with a term, or a sentence, stating
                precisely the duration of one's presence here: the way it is done in
                prison camps. That this doesn't happen suggests that the affair is not
                entirely human; that something we've got no idea or control of
                interferes. That there is an agency which is not subject to our
                chronology or, for that matter, our sense of virtue. Hence all these
                attempts to foretell or figure out one's future, hence one's reliance on
                physicians and gypsies, which intensifies once we are ill or in trouble,
                and which is but an attempt at domesticating - or demonizing - the
                divine. The same applies to our sentiment for beauty, natural and
                man-made alike, since the infinite can be appreciated only by the
                finite. Except for grace, the reasons for reciprocity would be
                unfathomable - unless one truly seeks a benevolent explanation of why
                they charge you so much for everything in this city.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" n="15">
                <p>By profession, or rather by the cumulative effect of \vhat I've been doing over the years , I am a writer; by trade, however, I am an academic, 
                    a teacher. The winter break at my school is five weeks long, and that's what in part explains the timing of my pilgrimages here - but only in 
                    part. What Paradise and vacation have in common is that you have to pay for both, and the coin is your previous life. Fittingly then, my 
                    romance with this city with this city in this particular season started long ago: long before I developed marketable skills, long before I 
                    could afford my passion.</p>
                <p>Sometime in 1966 I was twenty-six then a friend lent me three short novels by a French writer, Henri de Regnier, translated into Russian by 
                    the wonderful Russian poet Mikhail Kuzmin. All I knew about Regnier at that time was that he was one of the last Parnassians, a good poet but 
                    no great shakes. All I knew by heart of Kuzmin was a handful of his Alexandrian Songs and Clay Pigeons plus his reputation as a great aesthete, 
                    devout Orthodox, and avowed homosexual I think, in that order.</p>
                <p>By the time I'd got those novels, both their author and their translator were long dead. The books, too, were quite moribund: paperbacks, 
                    published in the late thirties, with no bindings to speak of, disintegrating in your palm. I remember neither their titles nor their publisher; 
                    in fact, I am quite vague on their respective plots also. Somehow I am under the impression that one of them was called Provincial Entertainments, 
                    but I am not sure. I could double- check, of course, but then the friend who lent them to me died a year ago; and I won't.</p>
                <p>They were a cross between picaresque and detective novels, and at least one of them, the one I call in my mind Provincial Entertainments, was 
                    set in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName> in winter. Its atmosphere was twilit and dangerous, its topography aggravated with mirrors; the main events were taking place on 
                    the other side of the amalgam, within some abandoned palazzo. Like many books of the twenties, it was fairly short some two hundred pages, no 
                    more and its pace was brisk. The subject was the usual: love and betrayal. The main thing: the book was written in short, page or 
                    page-and-a-halfchapters. From their pace came the sense of damp, cold, narrow streets through which one hurriesin the evening in a state of 
                    growing apprehension, turning left, turning right. For somebody with my birthplace, the city emerging from these pages was easily recognizable 
                    and felt like <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/498817">Petersburg</placeName>'s extension into a better history, not to mention latitude. However, what mattered for me most at the impressionable 
                    stage at which I came across this novel was that it taught me the most crucial lesson in composition; namely, that what makes a narrative good 
                    is not the story itself but what follows what. Unwittingly, I came to associate this principle with <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName>. If the reader now suffers, that's why.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="16">
                <p>Then one day another friend, who is still alive, brought me a disheveled issue ofLif magazine with a stunning color photo of <placeName>San Marco</placeName> covered 
                    with snow. Then a bit later a girl whom I was courting at thetime made me a birthday present of an accordion set of sepia postcards her 
                    grandmother had brought from a pre-revolutionary honeymoon in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName>, and I pored over it with my magnifying glass. Then my mother produced 
                    from God knows where a small square piece of cheap tapestry, a rag really, depicting the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/7627401">Palazzo Ducale</placeName>, and it covered the bolster on my 
                    Turkish sofa thus contracting the history of the republic under my frame. And throw into the bargain a little copper gondola brought by my 
                    father from his tour of duty in China, which my parents kept on their dressing table, filling it with loose buttons, needles, postage stamps, 
                    and increasingly pills and ampoules. Then the friend who gave me Regnier's novels and who died a year ago took me to a semiofficial screening 
                    ofthe smuggled, and for that reason black-and-white, copy of Visconti's Death in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName> with Dirk Bogarde. Alas, the movie wasn't much to speak 
                    of; besides, I never liked the novel much, either. Still, the long opening sequence with Mr. Bo- garde in a deck chair aboard a steamer made me forget about the interfering credits and regret 
                    that I was not mortally ill; even today I am still capable of feeling that regret.</p>
                <p>Then came the Veneziana. I began to feel that this city somehow was barging into focus, tottering on the verge of the three- dimensional. 
                    It was black-and-white, as befits something emerging from literature, or winter; aristocratic, darkish, cold, dimly lit, with twangs of 
                    Vivaldi and Cherubini in the background, with Bellini/Tiepolo/Titian-draped female bodies for clouds. And I vowed to myself that should I ever 
                    get out of my empire, should this eel ever escape the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2633321">Baltic</placeName>, the first thing I would do would be to come to <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName>, rent a room on the ground 
                    floor of some palazzo so that the waves raised by passing boats would splash against niy window, write a couple ofelegies while extinguishing 
                    my cigarettes on the damp stony floor, cough and drink, and,when the money got short, instead ofboarding a train, buy myself a little Browning 
                    and blow my brains out on the spot, unable to die in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName> of natural causes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="17">
                <p>Aperfectly decadent dream, of course; but at the age of twenty-eight everyone who's got some brains is a touch decadent. Besides, neither part 
                    of that project was feasible. So when at the age of thirty-two I all of a sudden found niysclf in the bowels of a different continent, in the 
                    middle of <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/6252001">America</placeName>, I used my first university salary to enact the better part of that dream and bought a round- trip ticket, 
                    <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/4990729">Detroit</placeName>-<placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3173435">Milano</placeName>-<placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/4990729">Detroit</placeName>. The plane was jammed with Italians employed by Ford and Chrysler and going home for Christmas. When the duty-free 
                    opened mid-flight, all of them rushed to the plane's rear, and for a moment I had a vision of a good old 707 flyingover the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3373405">Atlantic</placeName> 
                    crucifix-like: wings outstretched, tail down. Then there was the train ride with the only person I knew in the city at its end. The end was 
                    cold, damp, black-and-white. The city came into focus. <quote>"And the earth was without form, and void; and darkness was upon the face of the deep. 
                    And the Spirit of God moved upon the face of the waters,"</quote> to quote an author who visited here before. Then there was that next morning. It was 
                    Sunday, and all the bells were chiming.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="18">
                <p>I always adhered to the idea that God is time, or at least that His spirit is. Perhaps this idea was even of my own manufacture, but now I don't 
                    remember. In any case, I always thought that if the Spirit of God moved upon the face of the water, the water was bound to reflect it. Hence my 
                    sentiment for water, for its folds, wrinkles, and ripples,and  -  as I am a Northerner  -  for its grayness. I simply think that water is the image of 
                    time, and every New Year's Eve, in somewhat pagan fashion, I try to find myself near water, preferably near a sea or an ocean, to watch the 
                    emergence of a new helping, a new cupful of time from it. I am not looking for a naked maiden riding on a shell; I am looking for either a cloud 
                    or the crest of a wave hitting the shore at midnight. That, to me, is time coming out of water, and I stare at the lace-like pattern it puts on 
                    the shore, not with a gypsy-like knowing, but with tenderness and with gratitude.</p>
                <p>This is the way, and in my case the why, I set my eyes on this city. There is nothing Freudian to this fantasy, or specifically chor- date, 
                    although some evolutionary if not plainly atavistic or autobiographical connection could no doubt be established between the pattern a wave 
                    leaves upon the sand and its scrutiny by a descendant of the ichthyosaur, and a monster himself The upright lace of Venetian fasades is the 
                    best line time-alias-water has left on terra firma anywhere. Plus, there is no doubt a correspondence between  -  if not an outright dependence 
                    on - the rectangular nature of that lace's displays  -  i.e., local buildings  -  and the anarchy of water that spurns the notion of shape. It is as 
                    though space, cognizant here more than anyplace else of its inferiority to time, answers it with the only property time doesn't possess: with 
                    beauty. And that's why water takes this answer, twists it, wallops and shreds it, but ultimately carries it by and large intact off into 
                    the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3183462">Adriatic</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="19">
                <p>The eye in this city acquires an autonomy similar to that of a tear. The only difference is that it doesn't sever itself from the body but 
                    subordinates it totally. After a while  -  on the third or fourth day here  -  the body starts to regard itself as merely the eye's carrier, as a kind 
                    of submarine to its now dilating, now squinting periscope. Of course, for all its targets, its explosions are invariably self- inflicted: it's 
                    your own heart, or else your mind, that sinks; the eye pops up to the surface. This of course owes to the local topography, to the 
                    streets  -  narrow, meandering like eels -  that finally bring you to a flounder of a <foreign xml:lang="it">campo</foreign> with a cathedral in the middle of it, barnacled with 
                    saints and flaunting its Medusa-like cupolas. No matter what you set out for as you leave the house here, you are bound to get lost in these 
                    long, coiling lanes and passageways that beguile you to see them through, to follow them to their elusive end, which usually hits water, so 
                    that you can't even call it a cul-de- sac. On the map this city looks like two grilled fish sharing a plate, or perhaps like two nearly 
                    overlapping lobster claws (Pasternak compared it to a swollen croissant); but it has no north, south, east, or west; the only direction it has 
                    is sideways. It surrounds you like frozen seaweed, and the more you dart and dash about trying to get your bearings, the more you getlost. The 
                    yellow arrow signs at intersections are not much help either, for they, too, curve. In fact, they don't so much help you as kelp you. And in 
                    the fluently flapping hand of the native whom you stop to ask for directions, the eye, oblivious to his sputtering <foreign xml:lang="it">A destra, a sinistra, 
                    dritto, dritto</foreign>, readily discerns a fish.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="20">
                <p>A mesh caught in frozen seaweed might be a better metaphor. Because of the scarcity of space, people exist here in cellular proximity to one 
                    another, and life evolves with the immanent logic of gossip. One's territorial imperative in this city is circumscribed by water; the window 
                    shutters bar not so niuch daylight or noise (which is minimal here) as what may emanate from inside. When they are opened, shutters resemble 
                    the wings of angels prying into someone's sordid affairs, and like the spacing of the statues on cornices, human interplay here takes on 
                    theaspects of jewelry or, better yet, filigree. In these parts one is both more secretive and better informed than the police in tyrannies. No 
                    sooner do you cross the threshold of your apartment, especially in winter, than you fall prey to every conceivable surmise, fantasy, rumor. If 
                    you've got company, the next day at the grocery or newsagent you may meet a stare of biblical probing unfathomable, you would think, in a 
                    Catholic country. If you sue someone here, or vice versa, you must hire a lawyer on the outside. A traveler, of course, enjoys this sort of 
                    thing; the native doesn't. What a painter sketches, or an amateur photographs, is no fun for the citizen. Yet insinuation as a principle of 
                    city planning (which notion locally emerges only with the benefit of hindsight) is better than any modern grid and in tune with the local 
                    canals, taking their cue from water, which, like the chatter behind you, never ends. In that sense, brick is undoubtedly more potent than 
                    marble, although both are unassailable for a stranger. However, once or twice over theseseventeen years, I've managed to insinuate myself 
                    into a Venetian inner sanctum, into that beyond-the-anialgam labyrinth Regnier described in Provincial Entertainments. It happened in such a 
                    roundabout way that I can't even recall the details now, for I could not keep tabs on all those twists and turns that led to my passage into 
                    this labyrinth at the time. Somebody said something to somebody else, while the other person who wasn't even supposed to be there listened in 
                    and telephoned the fourth, as a result of which I'd been invited one night to a party given by the umpteenth at his palazzo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="21">
                <p>The palazzo had become the umpteenth's only recently, after nearly three centuries of legal battles fought by several branches of a family that 
                    had given the world a couple of Venetian admirals. Accordingly, two huge, splendidly carved aft-lanterns loomed in the two-story-high cave of 
                    the palazzo's courtyard, which was filled with all sorts of naval paraphernalia, dating from Renaissance days onward. The umpteenth himself, 
                    the last in the line, after decades and decades of waiting, had finally got it, to the great consternation of the other - apparently 
                    numerous - members of the family. He was no navy man; he was a bit of a playwright and a bit of a painter. For the moment, though, the most 
                    obvious thing about this forty-year-old  - a slim, short creature in a gray double- breasted suit of very good cut - was that he was quite sick. 
                    His skin looked post-hepatitis, parchment yellow - or perhaps it was just an ulcer. He ate nothing but consomme and boiled vegetables while his 
                    guests were gorging themselves on what would qualify as a separate chapter, if not a book.</p>
                <p>So the party was celebrating the umpteenth's having come into his own, as well as his launching a press to produce books about Venetian art. It 
                    was already in full swing when the three of us - a fellow writer, her son, and I - arrived. There were a lot of people: local and faintly 
                    international luminaries, politicos, nobles, the theater crowd, beards and ascots, mistresses of varying degrees of flamboyance, a bicycle 
                    star, American academics. Also, a bunch of giggling, agile, homosexual youths inevitable these days whenever something mildly spectacular takes 
                    place. They were presided over by a rather distraught and spiteful middle-aged queen - very blond, very blue- eyed, very drunk: the premises' 
                    major domo, whose days here were over and who therefore loathed everyone. Rightly so, I would add, given his prospects.</p>
                <p>As they were making quite a ruckus, the umpteenth politely offered to show the three of us the rest of the house. We readily agreed and went up 
                    by a small elevator. When we left its cabin, we left the twentieth, the nineteenth, and a large portion of the eighteenth century behind, or, 
                    more accurately, below: like sediment at the bottom of a narrow shaft.</p>
                <p>We found ourselves in a long, poorly lit gallery with a convex ceiling swarming with putti. No light would have helped anyway, as the walls were 
                    covered with large, floor-to- ceiling, dark-brownish oil paintings, definitely tailored to this space and separated by barely discernible 
                    marble busts and pilasters. The pictures depicted, as far as one could make out, sea and land battles, ceremonies, scenes from mythology; the 
                    lightest hue was wine-red. It was a mine of heavy porphyry in a state of abandonment, in a state of perpetual evening, with oils obscuring its 
                    ores; the silence here was truly geological. You couldn't ask, What is this? Who is this by? because of the incongruity of your voice, 
                    belonging to a later and obviously irrelevent organism. Or else it felt like an underwater journey - we were like a school of fish passing 
                    through a sunken galleon loaded with treasure, but not opening our mouths, since water would rush in.</p>
                <p>At the far end of the gallery our host flitted to the right, and we followed him into a room which appeared to be a cross between the library 
                    and the study of a seventeenth-century gentleman. Judging by the books behind the criss-crossed wire in the red, wardrobe-size wooden cabinet, 
                    the gentleman's century could even have been the sixteenth. There were about sixty fat, white, vellum-bound volumes, from Aesop to Zeno; just 
                    enough for a gentleman; more would turn him into a penseur, with disastrous consequences either for his manners or for his estate. Other than 
                    that, the room was quite bare. The light in it wasn't much better than in the gallery; I'd made out a desk and a large faded globe. Then our 
                    host turned a knob and I saw his silhouette framed by a door leading into an enfilade. I glanced at that enfilade and I shuddered: it looked 
                    like a vicious, viscous infinity. I swallowed air and stepped into it.</p>
                <p>It was a long succession of empty rooms. Rationally I knew that it couldn't be longer than the gallery parallel to which it ran. Yet it was. I 
                    had the sense of walking not so much in standard perspective as in a horizontal spiral where the laws ofoptics were suspended. Each room meant 
                    your further disappearance, the next degree of your nonexistence. This had to do with three things: drapery, mirrors, and dust. Although in 
                    some cases you could tell a room's designation - dining room, salon, possibly a nursery - most were similar in their lack of apparent function. 
                    They were about the same in size, or at any rate, they didn 't seem to differ much in that way from one another. And in each one ofthem windows 
                    were draped and two or three mirrors adorned the walls.</p>
                <p>Whatever the original color and pattern of the drapes had been, they now looked pale yellow and very brittle. A touch ofyour finger, let alone a 
                    breeze, would mean sheer destruction to them, as the shards of fabric scattered nearby on the parquet suggested. They were shedding, those 
                    curtains, and some of their folds exposed broad, bald, threadbare patches, as though the fabric felt it had come full circle and was now 
                    reverting to its pre-loom state. Our breath was perhaps too great an intimacy also; still, it was better than fresh oxygen, which, like 
                    history, the drapes didn't need. This was neither decay nor decomposition; this was dissipation back into time, where color and texture don't 
                    matter, where perhaps having learned what may happen to them, they will regroup and return, here or elsewhere, in a different guise. "Sorry," 
                    they seemed to say, "next time around we'll be more durable."</p>
                <p>Then there were those mirrors, two or three in each room, of various sizes, but mostly rectangular. They all had delicate golden frames, with 
                    well-wrought floral garlands or idyllic scenes which called more attention to themselves than to their surface, since the amalgam was invariably in poor shape. 
                    In a sense, the frames were more coherent than their contents, straining, as it were, to keep them from spreading over the wall. Having grown unaccustomed over 
                    the centuries to reflecting anything but the wall opposite, the mirrors were quite reluctant to return one's visage, out of either greed or 
                    impotence, and when they tried, one's features would come back incomplete. I thought, I begin to understand Regnier. From room to room, as we 
                    proceeded through the enfilade, I saw myself in those frames less and less, getting back more and more darkness. Gradual subtraction, I thought 
                    to myself; how is this going to end? And it ended in the tenth or eleventh room. I stood by the door leading into the next chamber, staring at 
                    a largish, three-by-four-foot gilded rectangle, and instead of myself I saw pitch-black nothing. Deep and inviting, it seemed to contain a 
                    perspective of its own - perhaps another enfilade. For a moment I felt dizzy; but as I was no novelist, I skipped the option and took a doorway.</p>
                <p>All along it had been reasonably ghostly; now it became unreasonably so. The host and my companions lagged somewhere behind; I was on my own. 
                    There was a great deal of dust everywhere; the hues and shapes of everything in sight were mitigated by its gray. Marble inlaid tables, 
                    porcelain figurines, sofas, chairs, the very parquet. Everything was powdered with it, and sometimes, as with figurines and busts, the effect 
                    was oddly beneficial, accentuating their features, their folds, the vivacity of a group. But usually its layer was thick and solid; what's more, 
                    it had an air of finality, as though no new dust could be added to it. Every surface craves dust, for dust is the flesh oftime, as a poet said, 
                    time's very flesh and blood; but here the craving seemed to be over. Now it will seep into the objects themselves, I thought, fuse with them, and 
                    in the end replace them. It depends of course on the material; some of it quite durable. They may not even disintegrate; they'll simply become 
                    grayer, as time would have nothing against assuming their shapes, the way it already had in this succession ofvacuum chambers in which it was 
                    overtaking matter.</p>
                <p>The last of them was the master bedroom. A gigantic yet uncovered four-poster bed dominated its space: the admiral's revenge for the narrow cot 
                    aboard his ship, or perhaps his homage to the sea itself. The latter was more probable, given the monstrous stucco cloud of putti descending on 
                    the bed and playing the role ofbaldachin. In fact, it was more sculpture than putti. The cherubs' faces were terribly grotesque: they all had 
                    these corrupt, lecherous grins as they stared - very keenly - downward upon the bed. They reminded me of that stable of giggling youths downstairs; 
                    and then I noticed a portable TV set in the corner of this otherwise absolutely bare room. I pictured the major domo entertaining his choice in 
                    this chamber: a writhing island ofnaked flesh amid a sea of linen, under the scrutiny of the dust- covered gypsum masterpiece. Oddly enough, I 
                    felt no repulsion. On the contrary, I felt that from time's point of view such entertainmenthere could only seem appropriate, as it generated 
                    nothing. After all, for three centuries, nothing here reigned supreme. Wars, revolutions, great discoveries, geniuses, plagues never entered 
                    here due to a legal problem. Causality was canceled, since its human carriers strolled in this perspective only in a caretaker capacity, once in 
                    a few years, if that. So the little wriggling shoal in the linen sea was, in fact, in tune with the premises, since it couldn't in nature give 
                    birth to anything. At best, the major domo's island - or should I say volcano? - existed only in the eyes ofthe putti. On the mirror's map it didn't. 
                    Neither did I.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="22">
                <p>That happened only once, although I've been told there are scores of places like this in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName>. But once is enough, especially in winter, 
                    when the local fog, the famous nebbia, renders this place more extern-poral than any palace's inner sanctum, by obliterating not only 
                    reflections but everything that has a shape: buildings, people, colonnades, bridges, statues. Boat services are canceled, airplanes neither 
                    arrive nor take off for weeks, stores are closed, and mail ceases to litter one's threshold. The effect is as though some raw hand had turned 
                    all those enfilades inside out and wrapped the lining around the city. Left, right, up, and down swap places, and you can find your way around 
                    only if you are a native or were given a cicerone. The fog is thick, blinding, and immobile. The latter aspect, however, is of advantage to you 
                    if you go out on a short errand, say, to get a pack of cigarettes, for you can find your way back via the tunnel your body has burrowed in the 
                    fog; the tunnel is likely to stay open for half an hour. This is a time for reading, for burning electricity all day long, for going easy on 
                    self- deprecating thoughts or coffee, for listening to the BBC World Service, for going to bed early.</p>
                <p>In short, a time for self-oblivion, induced by a city that has ceased to be seen. Unwittingly, you take your cue from it, especially if, like it, 
                    you've got no company. Having failed to be born here, you at least can take some pride in sharing its invisibility.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="23">
                <p>On the whole, however, I've always been as keen on the contents of this city's average brick affairs as on those of the marbled and unique. 
                    There is nothing populist, let alone anti-aristocratic, to this preference; nor is there anything of the novelist. It's just the echo of the 
                    sort of houses I've lived or worked in for most of my life. Failing to have been born here, I've failed, I suppose, a bit further by picking 
                    up a line of work which normally doesn't land one on a <foreign xml:lang="it">piano nobile</foreign>. On the other hand, there is perhaps some perverse snobbery in the 
                    sentiment for brick here, for its rank red akin to inflamed niuscle bared bythe scabs of peeled-otf stucco. Like eggs, which often - especially 
                    while I'm fixing myself breakfast - make me imagine the unknown civilization that came up with the idea of producing canned food in an organic 
                    fashion, brick and bricklaying somehow ring of an alternative order of flesh, not raw of course, but scarlet enough, and made up of small, 
                    identical cells. Yet another ofthe species' self-portraits at the elemental level, be it a \vall or a chimney. In the end, like the Almighty 
                    Himself, we make everything in our image, for want of a more reliable model; our artifacts tell more about ourselves than our confessions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="24">
                <p>At any rate, I seldom got myself across the thresholds of ordinary dwellings in this city. No tribe likes strangers, and Venetians are very 
                    tribal, in addition to being islanders. My Italian, \vildly oscillating around its firm zero, also remained a deterrent. It always got better 
                    after a month or so, but then I'd be boarding the plane that would remove me from the opportunity to use it for another year. Therefore, the 
                    company I kept was that of English-speaking natives and expatriate Americans whose houses shared a familiar version - if not degree - of affluence. 
                    As for those who spoke Russian, the characters from the local U, their sentiments toward the country of my birth and their politics used to 
                    bring me to the brink of nausea. The result would be nearly the same with the two or three local authors and academics: too many abstract 
                    lithographs on the walls, too many tidy bookshelves and African trinkets, silent wives, sallow daughters, conversations running their moribund 
                    course through current events, someone else's fame, psychotherapy, surrealism, down to the description of a shortcut to my hotel. Disparity of 
                    pursuits compromised by tautology of net results, if one needs a formula, that is. I aspired to wasting my afternoons in the empty office of 
                    some local solicitoror pharmacist, eyeing his secretary as she brought in coffee from a bar nearby, chatting idly away about the prices of 
                    motorboats or the redeeming features of Diocletian's character, since practically everyone here has a reasonably sound education as well as a 
                    yen for things streamlined. I'd be unable to lift myself from the chair, his clients would be few; in the end, he'd lock up the premises and 
                    we'd stroll to the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/6471043">Gritti</placeName> or <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/6471646">Danieli</placeName>, where I'd buy him drinks; if I was lucky, his secretary would join us. We'd sink in deep armchairs, 
                    exchanging malicious remarks about the new German battalions or the ubiquitous Japanese peeping through their cameras, like new elders , at 
                    the pallid naked marble thighs of this Susannahlike city wading cold, sunset-tinged, lapping waters. Later he might invite me over to his place 
                    for supper, and his pregnant wife, rising above the steaming pasta , would berate me volubly for my protracted bachelorhood . . . Too many 
                    neorealist movies, I suppose, too much Svevo-reading. For this sort of fantasyto come true, the requirements are the same as for inhabiting a 
                    <foreign xml:lang="it">piano nobile</foreign>. I don't meet them, nor have I ever stayed here long enough to abandon this pipe dream entirely. To have another life, one ought 
                    to be able to wrap up the first one, and the job should be done neatly. No one pulls this sort of thing off convincingly, though, at times, 
                    good services are rendered to one either by absconding spouses or by political systems . . . It's the other houses, strange staircases, odd 
                    smells, unfamiliar furniture and topography that the proverbial old dogs dream about in their senility and decrepitude, not new masters. 
                    And the trick is not to disturb them.</p>
                <p>So I never slept, let alone sinned, in a cast-iron family bed with pristine, crisp linen, embroidered and richly fringed bedspread, cloudlike 
                    pillows, and small pearl-encrusted crucifix above the headboard. I never trained my vacant stare on an oleograph of the Madonna, or faded pictures of a father/ brother/uncle/son in a <foreign xml:lang="it">bersagliere</foreign> helmet, with 
                    its black feathers, or chintz curtains on the window, or porcelain or majolica jug atop a dark wood chest of drawers filled with local lace, 
                    sheets, towels, pillowcases, and underclothes washed and ironed on the kitchen table by a young, strong, tanned, almost swarthy arm, as a 
                    shoulder strap slips off it and silver beads of sweat sparkle on the forehead. (Speaking of silver, it \vould in all likelihood be tucked away 
                    under a pile of sheets in one of those drawers.) All this, of course, is from a movie in which I was neither a star nor even an extra, from a 
                    movie \vhich for all I know they are not ever going to shoot again, or, if they do, the props will look different. In my mind, it is called 
                   <foreign xml:lang="it">Nozze di Seppia</foreign>, and it's got no plot to it, save a scene with me walking along the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/12689615">Fondamente Nuove</placeName> with the greatest watercolor in the world 
                    on the left and a red-brick infinity on the right. I should be wearing a cloth cap, dark serge jacket, and a white shirt with an open collar, 
                    washed and ironed by the same strong, tanned hand. Approaching the Arsenale, I'd turn right, cross twelve bridges, and take via Garibaldi to 
                    the Giardini, where, on an iron chair in the Caffe Paradiso, would be sitting she who washed and ironed this shirt six years ago. She'd have 
                    before her a glass of <foreign xml:lang="it">chinotto</foreign> and a <foreign xml:lang="it">panino</foreign>, a frayed little volume of Propertius' Monobiblos or Pushkin's Captain's Daughter; she'd be 
                    wearing a knee-length taffeta dress bought once in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3169070">Rome</placeName> on the eve of our trip to <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175455">Ischia</placeName>. She would lift her eyes, the color of mustard and 
                    honey, fix them on the figure in the heavy sergejacket, and say, "What a belly!" If anything is to save this picture from being a flop, it 
                    will be the winter light.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="25">
                    <p>A while ago I saw somewhere a photograph of a wartime execution. Three pale, skinny men of medium height and no specific facial features 
                        (they were seen by the camera in profile) stood on the edge ofa freshly dug ditch. They had a Northern appearance -  in fact, I think the 
                        photograph was taken in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/597427">Lithuania</placeName>. Close behind each one of them stood a German soldier holding a pistol. In the distance you could make 
                        out a bunch of other soldiers: the onlookers. It looked like early winter or late autumn, as the soldiers were in their winter overcoats. 
                        The condemned men, all three ofthem, were also dressed identically. They wore cloth caps, heavy blackjackets over white undershirts without 
                        collars: victims' uniform. On top of everything, they were cold. Partly because of that they drew their heads into their shoulders. In a 
                        second they will die: the photographer pushed his button an instant before the soldiers pulled their triggers. Thethree village lads drew 
                        their heads into their shoulders and \vere squinting the \vay a child does anticipating pain. They expected to be hurt, perhaps badly hurt; 
                        they expected the deafening - so close to their ears! - sound of a shot. And they squinted. Because the human repertoire of responses is so 
                        limited! What \vas coming to them \vas death, not pain; yet their bodies couldn't distinguish one from the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="26">
                    <p>One afternoon in November 1977, in the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/6480038">Londra</placeName>, where I was staying courtesy of the Biennale on Dissent, I received a phone call from Susan 
                        Sontag, who was staying in the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/6471043">Gritti</placeName> under the same dispensation. "Joseph," she said, "what are you doing this evening?" "Nothing," I said. 
                        "Why?" "Well, I bumped into Olga Rudge today in the piazza. Do you know her?" "No. You mean the Pound woman?" "Yes," said Susan, "and she invited 
                        me over tonight. I dread going there alone. Would you go with me, ifyou haven't got other plans?" I had none, and I said, Sure, I will, having 
                        understood her apprehension only too well. Mine, I thought, could be even greater. Well, to begin with, in my line of work Ezra Pound is a 
                        big deal, practically an industry. Many an American graphomaniac has found in Ezra Pound both a master and a martyr. As a young man, I had 
                        translated quite a bit of him into Russian. The translations were trash, but came very close to being published, courtesy ofsome 
                        crypto-Nazi on the board ofa solid literary magazine (now, ofcourse, the man is an avid nationalist). I liked the original for its 
                        sophomoric freshness and taut verse, for its thematic and stylistic diversity, for its voluminous cultural references, then out of my reach. 
                        I also liked his "make it new" dictum - liked it, that is, until I grasped that the true reason for making it new was that "it" was fairly old; 
                        that we were, after all, in a body shop. As for his plight in St. Elizabeths, in Russian eyes, that was nothing to rave about and, anyhow, 
                        better than the nine grams of lead that his wartime radio spiels might have earned him elsewhere. The Cantos, too, left me cold; the main 
                        error was an old one: questing after beauty. For someone with such a long record of residence in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175395">Italy</placeName>, it was odd that he hadn't realized 
                        that beauty can't be targeted, that it is always a by-product of other, often very ordinary pursuits. A fair thing to do, I thought, would 
                        be to publish both his poems and his speeches in one volume, without any learned introduction, and see what happens. Of all people, a poet 
                        should have known that time knows no distance between <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175456">Rapallo</placeName> and <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/597427">Lithuania</placeName>. I also thought that admitting that you've screwed up your life 
                        is more manly than persevering in the posture of a persecuted genius, with all the throwing up of the arm in a Fascist salute upon his 
                        return to <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175395">Italy</placeName>, subsequent disclaimers of the gesture's significance, reticent interviews, and cape and staff cultivating the appearance 
                        of a sage with the net result of resembling Haile Selassie. He was still big with some of my friends, and now I was to see his old woman.</p>
                    <p>The address given was in the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/7910703">Salute</placeName> sestiere, the part of town with the greatest, to my knowledge, percentage of foreigners in it, Anglos 
                        especially. After some meandering, we found the place - not too far, in fact, from the house in which Regnier dwelt in the teens of the 
                        century. We rang the bell, and the first thing I saw after the little woman with the beady eyes took shape on the threshold was the poet's 
                        bust by Gaudier-Brzeska sitting on the floor of the drawing room. The grip of boredom was sudden but sure.</p>
                    <p>Tea was served, but no sooner had we taken the first sip than the hostess - a gray-haired, diminutive, shipshape lady with many years in her 
                        to go - lifted her sharp finger, which slid into an invisible mental groove, and out of her pursed lips canie an aria the score of which 
                        has been in the public domain at least since 1945. That Ezra wasn't a Fascist; that they were afraid the Americans (which sounded pretty 
                        strange coming from an American) would put him in the chair; that he knew nothing about what was going on; that there were no Germans 
                        in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175456">Rapallo</placeName>; that he'd travel from <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175456">Rapallo</placeName> to <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3169070">Rome</placeName> only twice a month for the broadcast; that the Americans, again, were wrong to think 
                        that Ezra meant it to ... At some point I stopped registering what she was saying - which is easy for me, as English is not my mother 
                        tongue  -  and just nodded in the pauses, or whenever she'd punctuate her monologue with a tic-like "<foreign xml:lang="it">Capito?</foreign>" A record, I thought; her 
                        master's voice. Be polite and don't interrupt the lady; it's garbage, but she believes it. There is something in me, I suppose, that 
                        always respects the physical side of human utterance, regardless of the content; the very movement of someone's lips is more essential 
                        than what moves them. I sank deeper into my armchair and tried to concentrate on the cookies, as there was no dinner.</p>
                    <p>What woke me from my reverie was the sound of Susan's voice, which meant that the record had come to a stop. There was something odd in her 
                        timbre and I cocked my ear. Susan was saying, "But surely, Olga, you don't think that the Americans got cross with Ezra over his 
                        broadcasts. Because if it were only his broadcasts, then Ezra would be just another Tokyo Rose." Now, that was one of the greatest returns 
                        I had ever heard. I looked at Olga. It must be said that she took it like a mensch. Or, better yet, a pro. Or else she didn't grasp what 
                        Susan had said, though I doubt it. "What was it, then?" she inquired. "It was Ezra's anti-Semitism," replied Susan, and I saw the corundum 
                        needle of the old lady's finger once again hitting the groove. On this side of the record was: "One should realize that Ezra was not an 
                        anti-Semite; that after all his name was Ezra; that some of his friends were Jewish, including one Venetian admiral; that ..." The tune was 
                        equally familiar and equally long - about three-quarters of an hour; but this time we had to go. We thanked the old lady for the evening and 
                        bade her farewell. I, for one, did not feel the sadness one usually feels leaving the house ofa widow - or for that matter anybody alone in 
                        an empty place. The old lady was in good shape, reasonably well off; on top of that, she had the comfort of her convictions - a comfort, I 
                        felt, she'd go to any length to defend. I think I'd never met a Fascist - young or old; however, I'd dealt with a considerable number of old 
                        CP members, and that's why tea at Olga Rudge's place, with that bust of Ezra sitting on the floor, rang, so to speak, a bell. We turned to 
                        the left of the house and two minutes later found ourselves on the Fondamenta degli Incurabili.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="27">
                    <p>Ah, the good old suggestive power of language! Ah, this legendary
                        ability of words to imply more than reality can provide! Ah, the lock,
                        stock, and barrel of the mètier. Of course, the "Embankment of
                        the Incurables" harks back to the plague, to the epidemics that used to
                        sweep this city half clean century after century with a census taker's
                        regularity. The name conjures the hopeless cases, not so much strolling
                        along as scattered about on the flagstones, literally expiring,
                        shrouded, waiting to be carted - or, rather, shipped away. Torches,
                        fumes, gauze masks preventing inhalation, rustling of monks' frocks and
                        habits, soaring black capes, candles. Gradually the funereal procession
                        turns into a carnival, or indeed a promenade, where a mask would have to
                        be worn, since in this city everybody knows everybody. Add to this,
                        tubercular poets and composers; add to this, men of moronic convictions
                        or aesthetes hopelessly enamored of this place - and the Embankment
                        might earn its name, reality might catch up with language. And add to
                        this that the interplay between plague and literature (poetry in
                        particular, and Italian poetry especially) was quite intricate from the
                        threshold. That Dante's descent into the netherworld owes as much to
                        Homer's and Virgil's - episodic scenes, after all, in the Iliad and
                        the Aeneid - as to Byzantine medieval literature about cholera, with
                        its traditional conceit of premature burial and subsequent peregrination
                        of the soul. Overzealous agents of the netherworld bustling around the
                        cholera-stricken city would often zero in on a badly dehydrated body,
                        put their lips to his nostrils, and suck away his life spirit, thereby
                        proclaiming him dead and fit to be buried. Once underneath, the
                        individual would pass through infinite halls and chambers, pleading that
                        he has been consigned to the realm of the dead unjustly and seeking
                        redress. Upon obtaining it - usually by facing a tribunal presided over
                        by Hippocrates - he would return full of stories about those he had
                        bumped into in the halls and chambers below: kings, queens, heroes,
                        famous or infamous mortals of his time, repentant, resigned, defiant.
                        Sounds familiar? Well, so much for the suggestive powers of the
                        métier. One never knows what engenders what: an experience a
                        language, or a language an experience. Both are capable of generating
                        quite a lot. When one is badly sick, one imagines all sorts of
                        consequences and developments which, for all we know, won't ever take
                        place. Is this metaphoric thinking? The answer, I believe, is yes.
                        Except that when one is sick, one hopes, even against hope, to get
                        cured, the illness to stop. The end of an illness thus is the end of its
                        metaphors. A metaphor - or, to put it more broadly, language itself - is
                        by and large open-ended, it craves continuum: an afterlife, if you will.
                        In other words (no pun intended), metaphor is incurable. Add then to all
                        of this yourself, a carrier of this métier, or of this virus - in
                        fact, of a couple of them, sharpening your teeth for a third - shuffling
                        on a windy night along the Fondamenta, whose name proclaims your
                        diagnosis regardless of the nature of your malady.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="28">
                    <p>The winter light in this city! It has the extraordinary property ofenhancing your eye's power of resolution to the point of microscopic 
                        precision - the pupil, especially when it is of the gray or mustard-and-honey variety, humbles any Hasselblad lens and develops your 
                        subsequent memories to a National Geographic sharpness. The sky is brisk blue; the sun, escaping its golden likeness beneath the foot of 
                        <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3168290">San Giorgio</placeName>, sashays over the countless fish scales of the <foreign xml:lang="it">lagunas</foreign> lapping ripples; behind you, under the colonnades of the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/7627401">Palazzo Ducale</placeName>, 
                        a bunch of stocky fellows in fur coats are revving up Eine Kleine Nachtmusik, just for you, slumped in your white chair and squinting at 
                        the pigeons' maddening gambits on thechessboard of a vast <foreign xml:lang="it">campo</foreign>. The espresso at your cup's bottom is the one black dot in, you feel, a 
                        miles-long radius. Such are the noons here. In the morning this light breasts your windowpane and, having pried your eye open like a shell, 
                        runs ahead of you, strumming its lengthy rays - like a hot-footed schoolboy running his stick along the iron grate of a park or garden - along 
                        arcades, colonnades, redbrick chimneys, saints, and lions. "Depict! Depict!" it cries to you, either mistaking you for some Canaletto or 
                        Carpaccio or Guardi, or because it doesn't trust your retina's ability to retain what it makes available, not to mention your brain's 
                        capacity to absorb it. Perhaps the latter explains the former. Perhaps they are synonymous. Perhaps art is simply an organism's reaction 
                        against its retentive limitations. At any rate, you obey the command and grab your camera, supplementing both your brain cells and your 
                        pupil. Should this city ever be short of cash, it can go straight to Kodak for assistance - or else tax its products savagely. By the same 
                        token, as long as this place exists , as long as winter light shines upon it, Kodak shares are the best investment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="29">
                    <p>At sunset all cities look wonderful, but some more so than others. Reliefs become suppler, columns more rotund, capitals curlier, cornices 
                        more resolute, spires starker, niches deeper, disciples more draped, angels airborne. In the streets it gets dark, but it is still daytime 
                        for the Fondamenta and that gigantic liquid mirror where motorboats, va- poretti, gondolas, dinghies, and barges "like scattered old shoes" 
                        zealously trample Baroque and Gothic faqades, not sparing your own or a passing cloud's reflection either. "Depict it," whispers the winter 
                        light, stopped flat by the brick wall of a hospital or arriving home at the paradise of <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/7910497">San Zaccaria</placeName>'s jrontone after its long passage 
                        through the cosmos. And you sensethis light's fatigue as it rests in Zaccaria's marble shells for another hour or so, while the earth is 
                        turning its other cheek to the luminary. This is the winter light at its purest. It carries no warmth or energy, having shed them and left 
                        them behind somewhere in the universe, or in the nearby cumulus. Its particles' only ambition is to reach an object and make it, big or 
                        small, visible. It's a private light, the light of Giorgione or Bellini, not the light of Tiepolo or Tintoretto. And the city lingers in it, 
                        savoring its touch, the caress of the infinity whence it came. An object, after all, is what makes infinity private.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="30">
                    <p>And the object can be a little monster, with the head of a lion and the body ofa dolphin. The latter would coil, the former gnash its fangs. 
                        It could adorn an entrance or simply burst out of a wall without any apparent purpose, the absence of which would make it oddly 
                        recognizable. In a certain line of work, and at a certain age, nothing is more recognizable than a lack of purpose. The same goes for a 
                        fusion oftwo or more traits or properties, not to mention genders. On the whole, all these nightmarish creatures - dragons, gargoyles, 
                        basilisks, female-breasted sphinxes, winged lions, Cerberuses, Minotaurs, centaurs, chimeras - that come to us from mythology (which, by 
                        rights, should have the status of classical surrealism) are our self-portraits, in the sense that they denote the species' genetic memory 
                        of evolution. Small wonder that here, in this city sprung from water, they abound. Again, there is nothing Freudian to them, nothing sub or 
                        unconscious. Given the nature of human reality, the interpretation of dreams is a tautology and at best could bejustified only by 
                        daylight's ratio to darkness. It's doubtful, though, that this democratic principle is operational in nature, where nothing enjoys a 
                        majority. Not even water, though it reflects and refracts everything, including itself, alternating forms and substances, sometimes 
                        gently, sometimes monstrously. That's what accounts for the quality of winter light here; that's what explains its fondness for little 
                        monsters, as well as for cherubs. Presumably cherubs, too, are part of the species' evolution. Or else it is the other way around, for if 
                        one was to take their census in this city, they might outnumber the natives.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="31">
                <p>Monsters, however, command more of one's attention. If only because this term has been hurled at one more frequently than the other; if only 
                    because in our parts one gains wings only in the air force. One's guilty conscience would be enough to identify oneself with any of these 
                    marble, bronze, or plaster concoctions - withthe dragon, to say the least, rather than with San Giorgio. In a line of work involving the dipping 
                    of a pen into an inkpot, one can identify with both. After all, there is no saint without a monster - not to mention the ink's octopal affinity. 
                    But even without reflecting upon or refracting this idea, it is clear that this is a city of fish, caught and swimming around alike. And seen 
                    by a fish - endowed, let's say, with a human eye, in order to avoid its own famous distortion - man would appear a monster indeed; not an octopus, 
                    perhaps, but surely a quadropus. Something, to say the least, far more complex than the fish itself. Small wonder, then, that sharks are after 
                    us so much. Should one ask a simple <foreign xml:lang="it">orata</foreign> not even a caught one, in a free state - what it thinks one looks like, it will reply, You are a 
                    monster. And the conviction in its voice will be oddly familiar, as though its eye is of the mustard- and-honey variety.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="32">
                <p>So you never know as you move through these labyrinths whether you are pursuing a goal or running from yourself, whether you are the hunter or 
                    his prey. Surely not a saint, but perhaps not yet a full-scale dragon; hardly a Theseus, but not a maiden- starved Minotaur either. The Greek 
                    version rings, though, a better bell, since the winner gets nothing, because the slayer and the slain are related. The monster, after all, 
                    was the prize's half brother; in any case, he was half brother to the hero's eventual wife. Ariadne and Phacdra were sisters, and for all we 
                    know, the brave Athenian had them both. In fact, with an eye on marrying into the Cretan king's family, he niight have accepted the murderous 
                    commission to make the family more respectable. As granddaughters of Helios, the girls were supposed to be pure and shining; their names 
                    suggested as much. Why, even their mother, Pasiphae, was, for all her dark urges, Blindingly Bright. And perhaps she yielded to those dark 
                    urges and did it with the bull precisely to prove that nature neglects the majority principle, since the bull's horns suggest the moon. 
                    Perhaps she was interested in chiaroscuro rather than in bestiality and eclipsed the bull for purely optical reasons. And the fact that the 
                    bull, whose symbolism-laden pedigree ran all the way back to cave paintings, was blind enough to mistake the artificial cow Daedalus built for 
                    Pasiphae on this occasion is her proof that her ancestry still holds the upper hand in the system of causality, that Helios' light, refracted 
                    in her, Pasiphae, is still - after four children (two fine daughters and two good-for-nothing boys) - blindingly bright. As far as the principle 
                    ofcausality is concerned, it should be added that the main hero in this story is precisely Daedalus, who, apart from a very convincing cow, 
                    built - this time on the king's request - the very labyrinth in which the bull-headed offspring and his slayer got to face each other one day, 
                    with disastrous consequences for the former. In a manner of speaking, the whole business is Daedalus' brain child, the labyrinth especially, 
                    as it resembles a brain. In a manner of speaking, everybody is related to everybody, the pursuer to the pursued, at least. Small wonder, then, 
                    that one's ineanderings through the streets of this city, whose biggest colony for nearly three centuries was the island of Crete, feels 
                    somewhat tautological, especially as light fades - that is, especially as its pasiphaian, ariadnan, and phaedran properties fail. In other 
                    words, especially in the evening, when one loses oneself to self-deprecation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="33">
                <p>On the brighter side there are, ofcourse, lots oflions: winged ones, with their books opened on <quote>"Peace upon you, St. Mark the Evangelist,"</quote> or 
                    lions of regular feline appearance. The winged ones, strictly speaking, belong in the category ofmonsters, too. Givenmy occupation, however, 
                    I've always regarded them as a more agile and literate form of Pegasus, who can surely fly, but whose ability to read is somewhat more doubtful. 
                    A paw, at any rate, is a better instrument for turning pages than a hoof. In this city the lions are ubiquitous, and over the years I've 
                    unwittingly come to share this toteni to the point of placing one of theni on the cover of one of my books: the closest a man gets in niy line of 
                    work to having his own fac;ade. Yet monsters they are, if only because they are products of the city's fantasy, since even at the zenith of this 
                    republic's maritime might it controlled no territory where this animal could be found even in its wingless state. (The Greeks were more on the 
                    dot with their bull, its neolithic pedigree notwithstanding.) As for the Evangelist himself, he of course died in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/361058">Alexandria, Egypt</placeName> - but of 
                    natural causes - and he never went on a safari. In general, Christendom's truck with lions is negligible, as they could not be found in its domain, 
                    dwelling solely in Africa, and in deserts at that. This of course helped toward their subsequent association with desert fathers; other than that, 
                    the Christians could have encountered the animal only as its diet in Roman circuses, where lions were imported from African shores for entertainment. 
                    Their unfa- miliarity - better to say, their nonexistence -  was what would unleash the ancients' fantasy, enabling them to attribute to the animals 
                    various aspects of othenvorldliness, including those of divine commerce. So it's not entirely wild to have this animal sitting on Venetian faqades in 
                    the unlikely role of the guardian of St. Mark's eternal repose; if not the Church, then the city itself could be seen as a lioness protecting its cub. 
                    Besides, in this city, the Church and the state have merged, in a perfectly Byzantine fashion. The only case, I must add, where such a merger turned 
                    out - quite early on - to be to the subjects' advantage. No wonder, then, that the place was literally lionized, that the lion itself got lionized, which 
                    is to say humanized. On every cornice, overnearly every entrance, you see either its muzzle, with a human look, or a human head with leonine features. 
                    Both, in the final analysis, qualify as monsters (albeit of the benevolent sort), since neither ever existed. Also, because of their numerical 
                    superiority over any other carved or sculpted image, including that of the Madonna or the Redeemer Himself. On the other hand, it's easier to carve a 
                    beast than a human figure. Basically, the animal kingdom fared poorly in Christian art - not to mention the doctrine. So the local pride of Felidae may 
                    regard itself as their kingdom's way of getting even. In winter, they brighten one's dusk.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="34">
                    <p>Once, in a dusk that darkened gray pupils but brought gold to those of the mustard-cum- honey variety, the owner of the latter and I 
                        encountered an Egyptian warship - a light cruiser, to be precise - moored at the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/7910812">Fondamenta dell'Arsenale</placeName>, near the Giardini. I can't recall 
                        its name now, but its home port was definitely <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/361058">Alexandria</placeName>. It was a highly modern piece ofnaval hardware, bristling with all sorts of 
                        antennae, radar, satellite dishes, rocket launchers, antiaircraft turrets, etc., apart from the usual large-caliber guns. From a distance 
                        you couldn't tell its nationality. Even close up you could be confused, because the uniforms and general deportment ofthe crew aboard 
                        looked vaguely British. The flag was already lowered, and the sky over the lagtma was changing from Bordeaux to dark porphyry. As we 
                        marveled at the nature of the errand that brought this man-of-war here - a need for repairs? a new courtship between <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName> and <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/361058">Alexandria</placeName>? 
                        to reclaim the holv relic stolen from the latter in the twelfth century? - its loudspeakers suddenly came to life and we heard, 
                        "Allah! Akbar Allah! Akbar!" The muezzin was calling the crew to evening prayer, the ship's t\vo niasts momentarilyturning to minarets. 
                        All at once the cruiser was <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/745042">Istanbul</placeName> in profile. I felt that the map had suddenly folded or the book of history had shut before my eyes. 
                        At least that it had become six centuries shorter: Christianity was no longer Islam's senior. The Bosporus was overlapping the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3183462">Adriatic</placeName>, 
                        and you couldn't tell which wave was which. A far cry from architecture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="35">
                    <p>On winter evenings the sea, welled by a contrary easterly, fills every canal to the brim like a bathtub, and at times overflows them. Nobody 
                        runs up from downstairs crying, "The pipes!" as there is no downstairs. The city stands ankle-deep in water, and boats, <quote>"hitched like 
                        animals to the walls,"</quote> to quote Cassiodorus, prance. The pilgrim's shoe, having tested the water, is drying atop his hotel room's 
                        radiator; the native dives intohis closet to fish out his pair of rubber boots. "<foreign xml:lang="it">Acqua alta</foreign>," says a voice over the radio, and human 
                        traffic subsides. Streets empty; stores, bars, restaurants and trattorias close. Only their signs continue burning, finally getting a piece 
                        of the narcissistic action as the pavement briefly, superficially, catches up with the canals. Churches, however, remain open, but then 
                        treading upon water is no news to either clergy or parishioners; neither to music, water's twin.</p>
                    <p>Seventeen years ago, wading aimlessly through one <foreign xml:lang="it">campo</foreign> after another, a pair ofgreen rubber boots brought nie to the threshold of a 
                        smallish pink edifice. On its wall I saw a plaque saying that Antonio Vivaldi, prematurely born, was baptized in this church. In those 
                        days I was still reasonably red-haired; I felt sentimental about bumping into the place of baptism of that "red cleric" who has given me so 
                        muchjoy on so many occasions and in so many godforsaken parts of the world. And I seemedto recall that it was Olga Rudge who had organized 
                        the first-ever Vivaldi <foreign xml:lang="it">settimana</foreign> in this city - as it happened, just a few days before World War II broke out. It took place, somebody told 
                        me, in the palazzo of the Countess Polignac, and Miss Rudge was playing the violin. As she proceeded with the piece, she noticed out of 
                        the corner of her eye that a gentleman had entered the <foreign xml:lang="it">salone</foreign> and stood by the door, since all the seats were taken. The piece was long, 
                        and now she felt somewhat worried, because she was approaching a passage where she had to turn the page without interrupting her play. The 
                        man in the corner of her eye started to move and soon disappeared from her field of vision. The passage grew closer, and her nervousness 
                        grew, too. Then, at exactly the point where she had to turn the page, a hand emerged from the left, stretched to the niusic stand, and 
                        slowly turned the sheet. She kept playing and, when the difficult passage was over, lifted her eyes to theleft to acknowledge her 
                        gratitude. "And that," Olga Rudge told a friend of niine, "is how I first met Stravinsky."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="36">
                <p>So you may enter and stand through the service. The singing will be a bit subdued, presumably on account of the weather. If you can excuse 
                        it in this way, so, no doubt, will its Addressee. Besides, you can't follow it that well, whether it's in Italian or Latin. So you just 
                        stand or take a pew in the rear and listen. <quote>"The best way to hear Mass,"</quote> Wystan Auden used to say, <quote>"is when you don't know the language."</quote> 
                        True, ignorance helps concentration on such occasions no less than the poor lighting from which the pilgrim suffers in every Italian 
                        church, especially in winter. Dropping coins into an illumination box while the service is in progress is not nice. What's more, you 
                        often don't have enough of them in your pocket to appreciate the picture fully. In days ofyore I carried with me a powerful, 
                        New-York-City-Police-Department- issue flashlight. One way to get rich, I thought, would be to start manufacturing miniature flashbulbs 
                        like those they mount on cameras, but of great duration. I'd call it "Lasting Flash," or, better yet, "<foreign xml:lang="la">Fiat Lux</foreign>", and in a couple of years 
                        I'd buy an apartment somewhere in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/9175974">San Lio</placeName> or <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/7910703">Salute</placeName>. I'd even marry my partner's secretary, which he doesn't have since he doesn't 
                        exist . . . The music subsides; its twin, however, has risen, you discover upon stepping outside - not significantly, but enough for you 
                        to feel reimbursed for the faded chorale. For water, too, is choral, in more ways than one. It is the same water that carried the 
                        Crusaders, the merchants, St. Mark's relics, Turks, every kind of cargo, military, or pleasure vessel; above all, it reflected everybody 
                        who ever lived, not to mention stayed, in this city, everybody who ever strolled or waded its streets in the way you do now. Small wonder 
                        that it looks muddy green in the daytime and pitch black at night, rivaling the firmament. A miracle that, rubbed the right and the wrong 
                        way for over a millennium, it doesn't have holes in it, that it is still H2O, though you would never drink it; that it still rises. It 
                        really does look like musical sheets, frayed at the edges, constantly played, coming to you in tidal scores, in bars of canals with 
                        innumerable obbligati of bridges, mullioned windows, or curved crownings of Coducci cathedrals, not to mention the violin necks of
                        gondolas. In fact, the whole city, especially at night, resembles a gigantic orchestra, with dimly lit music stands of palazzi, with a 
                        restless chorus of waves, with the falsetto of a star in the winter sky. The music is, of course, greater than the band, and no hand can 
                        turn the page.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="37">
                <p>That's what worries the band, or more exactly, its conductors, the city fathers. According to their calculations, this city, during this century 
                    alone, has sagged twenty-three centimeters. So what appears spectacular to the tourist is a full-scale headache for the native. And if it were 
                    only a headache, that would be fine. But the headache is crowned with an increasing apprehension, not to say fear, that what lies in store for 
                    the city is the fate of Atlantis. The fear is not without foundation, and not only because the city's uniqueness does amount to a civilization 
                    of its own. The main danger is perceived to be high winter tides; the rest is done by the mainland's industry and agriculture silting the 
                    <foreign xml:lang="it">laguna</foreign> with their chemical wastes, and by the deterioration of the city's own clogged canals. In my line of work, though, ever since the 
                    Romantics, human fault has appeared to be a likelier culprit when it comes to disaster than any <foreign xml:lang="it">forza deldestino</foreign>. (That an insurance man can 
                    tell these two a part is indeed a feat of imagination.) So, prey to tyrannical impulses, I would install some sort of flap gate to stem the 
                    sea of humanity, which has swelled in the last two decades by two billion and whose crest is its refuse. I'd freeze the industry and the 
                    residence in the twenty-mile zone along the northern shore of the drag and dredge the city's canals (I'd either use the military to carry out 
                    this operation or pay local companies double time) and seed them with fish and the right kind of bacteria to keep them clean.</p>
                <p>I have no idea what kind of fish or bacteria these are, but I'm pretty sure they exist: tyranny is seldom synonymous with expertise. At any 
                    rate, I'd call Sweden andask the Stockholm municipality for advice: in that city, with all its industry and population, the moment you step 
                    out of your hotel, the salmon leap out of the water to greet you. If it is the difference in temperature that does it, then one could 
                    try dumping blocks ofice into the canals or, failing that, routinely void the natives' freezers of ice cubes, since whiskey is not very much 
                    in vogue here, not even in winter.</p>
                <p>"Why, then, do you go there at such a season?" my editor asked me once, sitting in a Chinese restaurant in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName> with his gay English 
                    charges. "Yes, why do you?" they echoed their prospective benefactor. "What is it like there in winter?" I thought of telling them about <foreign xml:lang="it">acqua alta</foreign>;
                    about the various shades of gray in the window as one sits at breakfast in one's hotel, enveloped by silence and the mealy morning 
                    pall ofnewlyweds' faces; about pigeons accentuating every curve and cornice of the local Baroque in their dormant affinity for architecture; 
                    about a lonely monument to Francesco Querini and his two huskies carved out of Istrian stone similar, I think, in its hue, to what he saw last, 
                    dying, on his ill-fated journey to the North Pole, now listening to the Giardini's rustle of evergreens in the company of Wagner and Carducci; 
                    about a brave sparrow perching on the bobbing blade of a gondola against the backdrop of a sirocco- roiled damp infinity. No, I thought, 
                    looking at their effete but eager faces; no, that won't do. "Well," I said, "it's like Greta Garbo swimming."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="38">
                <p>Over these years, during my long stays and brief sojourns here, I
                    have been, I think, both happy and unhappy in nearly equal measure. It
                    didn't matter which, if only because I came here not for romantic
                    purposes but to work, to finish a piece, to translate, to write a couple
                    of poems, provided I could be that lucky; simply to be. That is, neither
                    for a honeymoon (the closest I ever came to that was many years ago, on
                    the island of Ischia, or else in Siena) nor for a divorce. And so I
                    worked. Happiness or unhappiness would simply come in attendance,
                    although sometimes they'd stay longer than I did, as if waiting on me.
                    It is a virtue, I came to believe long ago, not to make a meal out of
                    one's emotional life. There's always enough work to do, not to mention
                    that there's world enough outside. In the end, there's always this city.
                    As long as it exists, I don't believe that I, or, for that matter,
                    anyone, can be mesmerized or blinded by romantic tragedy. I remember one
                    day - the day I had to leave after a month here alone. I had just had
                    lunch in some small trattoria on the remotest part of the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/12689615">Fondamente
                    Nuove</placeName>, grilled fish and half a bottle of wine. With that inside, I set
                    out for the place I was staying, to collect my bags and catch a
                    vaporetto. I walked a quarter of a mile along the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/12689615">Fondamente Nuove</placeName>, a
                    small moving dot in that gigantic watercolor, and then turned right by
                    the hospital of Giovanni e Paolo. The day was warm, sunny, the sky blue,
                    all lovely. And with my back to the Fondamente and <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3167976">San Michele</placeName>, hugging
                    the wall of the hospital, almost rubbing it with my left shoulder and
                    squinting at the sun, I suddenly felt: I am a cat. A cat that has just
                    had fish. Had anyone addressed me at that moment, I would have meowed. I
                    was absolutely, animally happy. Twelve hours later, of course, having
                    landed in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>, I hit the worst possible mess in my life - or the
                    one that appeared that way at the time. Yet the cat in me lingered; had
                    it not been for that cat, I'd be climbing the walls now in some
                    expensive institution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="39">
                <p>At night, there is not much to do here. Opera and church recitals
                    are options, of course, but they require some initiative and
                    arrangement: tickets and schedules and so forth. I am not good at that;
                    it's rather like fixing a three-course meal all for yourself - perhaps
                    even lonelier. Besides, my luck is such that whenever I considered an
                    evening at La Fenice, they would be having a week-long run of
                    Tchaikovsky or Wagner - equals, as far as my allergy is concerned. Never
                    once Donizetti or Mozart! That leaves reading and strolling dully along,
                    which is about the same, since at night these narrow stony gennels are
                    like passages between the bookshelves of some immense, forgotten
                    library, and equally quiet. All the "books" are shut tight, and you
                    guess what they are about only by the names on their spines, under the
                    doorbell. Oh, there you can find your Donizettis and Rossinis, your
                    Lullys and Frescobaldis! Maybe even a Mozart, maybe even a Haydn. Or
                    else these streets are like wardrobe racks: all the clothes are of dark,
                    peeling fabric, but the lining is ruby and shimmering gold. Goethe
                    called this place the "republic of beavers," but perhaps Montesquieu
                    with his resolute "<quote><foreign xml:lang="fr">un endroit ou il devrait n'avoir que des poissons</foreign></quote>"
                    was more on the mark. For, now and then, across the canal, two or three
                    well-lit, tall, rounded windows, half shaded with gauze or tulle, reveal
                    an octopal chandelier, the lacquered fin of a grand piano, opulent
                    bronze framing auburn or rubescent oils, the gilded rib cage of a
                    ceiling's beams - and you feel as though you are looking into a fish
                    through its scales, and inside of it there's a party.</p>
	            <p>At a distance - across a canal - you can hardly tell the guests from
                    their hostess. With all due respect to the best available creed, I must
                    say I don't think this place has evolved from the famous chordate only,
                    triumphant or not. I suspect and submit that, in the first place, it
                    evolved from the very element that gave that chordate life and shelter
                    and which, for me at least, is synonymous with time. The element comes
                    in many shapes and hues, with many different properties apart from those
                    of Aphrodite and the Redeemer: lull, storm, crest, wave, froth, ripple,
                    etc., not to mention the marine organisms. In my mind, this city limns
                    all discernible patterns of the element and its contents. Splashing,
                    glittering, glowing, glinting, the element has been casting itself
                    upward for so long that it is not surprising that some of these aspects
                    eventually acquired mass, flesh, and grew solid. Why it should have
                    happened here, I have no idea. Presumably because the element here had
                    heard Italian.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="40">
                <p>The eye is the most autonomous of our organs. It is so because the
                    objects of its attention are inevitably situated on the outside. Except
                    in a mirror, the eye never sees itself. It is the last to shut down when
                    the body is falling asleep. It stays open when the body is stricken with
                    paralysis or dead. The eye keeps registering reality even when there is
                    no apparent reason for doing this, and under all circumstances. The
                    question is: Why? And the answer is: Because the environment is hostile.
                    Eyesight is the instrument of adjustment to an environment which remains
                    hostile no matter how well you have adjusted to it. The hostility of the
                    environment grows proportionately to the length of your presence in it,
                    and I am speaking not of old age only. In short, the eye is looking for
                    safety. That explains the eye's predilection for art in general and
                    Venetian art in particular. That explains the eye's appetite for beauty,
                    as well as beauty's own existence. For beauty is solace, since beauty is
                    safe. It doesn't threaten you with murder or make you sick. A statue of
                    Apollo doesn't bite, nor will Carpaccio's poodle. When the eye fails to
                    find beauty - alias solace - it commands the body to create it, or,
                    failing that, adjusts itself to perceive virtue in ugliness. In the
                    first instance, it relies on human genius; in the second, it draws on
                    one's reservoir of humility. The latter is in greater supply, and like
                    every majority tends to make laws. Let's have an illustration; let's
                    take a young maiden. At a certain age one eyes passing maidens without
                    applied interest, without aspiring to mount them. Like a TV set left
                    switched on in an abandoned apartment, the eye keeps sending in images
                    of all these 5'8'' miracles, complete with light chestnut hair, Perugino
                    ovals, gazelle eyes, nurse-like bosoms, wasp waists, dark-green velvet
                    dresses, and razor-sharp tendons. An eye may zero in on them in a church
                    at someone's wedding or, worse still, in a bookstore's poetry section.
                    Reasonably farsighted or resorting to the counsel of the ear, the eye
                    may learn their identities (which come with names as breathtaking as,
                    say, Arabella Ferri) and, alas, their dishearteningly firm romantic
                    affiliations. Regardless of such data's uselessness, the eye keeps
                    collecting it. In fact, the more useless the data, the sharper the
                    focus. The question is why, and the answer is that beauty is always
                    external; also, that it is the exception to the rule. That's what - its
                    location and its singularity - sends the eye oscillating wildly or - in
                    militant humility's parlance - roving. For beauty is where the eye
                    rests. Aesthetic sense is the twin of one's instinct for
                    self-preservation and is more reliable than ethics. Aesthetics' main
                    tool, the eye, is absolutely autonomous. In its autonomy, it is inferior
                    only to a tear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="41">
                <p>A tear can be shed in this place on several occasions. Assuming that
                    beauty is the distribution of light in the fashion most congenial to
                    one's retina, a tear is an acknowledgment of the retina's, as well as
                    the tear's, failure to retain beauty. On the whole, love comes with the
                    speed of light; separation, with that of sound. It is the deterioration
                    of the greater speed to the lesser that moistens one's eye. Because one
                    is finite, a departure from this place always feels final; leaving it
                    behind is leaving it forever. For leaving is a banishment of the eye to
                    the provinces of the other senses; at best, to the crevices and
                    crevasses of the brain. For the eye identifies itself not with the body
                    it belongs to but with the object of its attention. And to the eye, for
                    purely optical reasons, departure is not the body leaving the city but
                    the city abandoning the pupil. Likewise, disappearance of the beloved,
                    especially a gradual one, causes grief no matter who, and for what
                    peripatetic reason, is actually in motion. As the world goes, this city
                    is the eye's beloved. After it, everything is a letdown. A tear is the
                    anticipation of the eye's future.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="42">
                <p>To be sure, everybody has designs on her, on this city. Politicians
                    and big businesses especially, for nothing has a greater future than
                    money. It is so much so that money feels synonymous with the future and
                    tries to order it. Hence the wealth of frothy outpourings about
                    revamping the city, about turning the entire province of Veneto into a
                    gateway to Central Europe, about boosting the region's industry,
                    expanding the harbor complex at <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3173960">Marghera</placeName>, increasing the oil-tanker
                    traffic in the <foreign xml:lang="it">laguna</foreign> and deepening the <foreign xml:lang="it">laguna</foreign> for the same
                    purposes, about converting the Venetian Arsenale, immortalized by Dante,
                    into the Beaubourg's spitting - literally - image for storing the most
                    recently discharged phlegm, about housing an Expo here in the year 2000,
                    etc. All this drivel normally gushes out of the same mouth, and often on
                    the same breath, that blabbers about ecology, protection, restoration,
                    cultural patrimony, and whatnot. The goal of all that is one: rape. No
                    rapist, though, wants to regard himself as such, let alone get caught.
                    Hence the mixture of objectives and metaphors, high rhetoric and lyrical
                    fervor swelling the barrel chests of parliamentary deputies and
                    <foreign xml:lang="it">commendatore</foreign> alike.</p>
	            <p>Yet while these characters are far more dangerous - indeed more
                    harmful - than the Turks, the Austrians, and Napoleon all lumped
                    together, since money has more battalions than generals, in the
                    seventeen years that I've frequented this city very little has changed
                    here. What saves <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName>, like Penelope, from her suitors is their
                    rivalry, the competitive nature of capitalism boiled down to fat cats'
                    blood relations to different political parties. Lobbing spanners into
                    each other's machinery is something democracy is awfully good at, and
                    the leapfrogging of Italian cabinets has proved to be the city's best
                    insurance. So has the mosaic of the city's own political jigsaw. There
                    are no doges anymore, and the 80,000 dwellers of these 118 islands are
                    guided not by the grandeur of some particular vision but by their
                    immediate, often nearsighted concerns, by their desire to make ends
                    meet.</p>
	            <p>Farsightedness here, however, would be counterproductive. In a place
                    this size, twenty or thirty people out of work are the city council's
                    instant headache, which, apart from islands' innate mistrust of the
                    mainland, makes for a poor reception of the latter's blueprints, however
                    breathtaking. Appealing as they may be elsewhere, promises of universal
                    employment and growth make little sense in a city barely eight miles in
                    circumference, which even at the apogee of its maritime fortunes never
                    exceeded 200,000 souls. Such prospects may thrill a shopkeeper or
                    perhaps a doctor; a mortician, though, would object, since the local
                    cemeteries are jammed as it is and the dead now should be buried on the
                    mainland. In the final analysis, that's what the mainland is good for.</p>
	            <p>Still, had the mortician and the doctor belonged to different
                    political parties, that would be fine, some progress could be made. In
                    this city, they often belong to the same, and things get stalled rather
                    early, even if the party is the PCI. In short, underneath all these
                    squabbles, unwitting ones or otherwise, lies the simple truth that
                    islands don't grow. That's what money, a.k.a. the future, a.k.a. voluble
                    politicos and fat cats, can't take, fails to grasp. What's worse, it
                    feels defied by this place, since beauty, a <foreign xml:lang="fr">fait accompli</foreign> by
                    definition, always defies the future, regarding it as nothing so much as
                    an overblown, impotent present, or as its fading ground. If this place
                    is reality (or, as some claim, the past), then the future with all its
                    aliases is excluded from it. At best, it amounts to the present. And
                    perhaps nothing proves this better than modern art, whose poverty alone
                    makes it prophetic. A poor man always speaks for the present, and
                    perhaps the sole function of collections like Peggy Guggenheim's and the
                    similar accretions of this century's stuff habitually mounted here is to
                    show what a cheap, self-assertive, ungenerous, one-dimensional lot we
                    have become, to instill humility in us: there is no other outcome
                    thinkable against the background of this Penelope of a city, weaving her
                    patterns by day and undoing them by night, with no Ulysses in sight.
                    Only the sea.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="43">
                <p>I think it was Hazlitt who said that the only thing that could beat
                    this city of water would be a city built in the air. That was a
                    Calvinoesque idea, and who knows, as an upshot of space travel, that may
                    yet come to pass. As it is, apart from the moon landing, this century
                    may be best remembered by leaving this place intact, by just letting it
                    be. I, for one, would advise even against gentle interference. Of
                    course, film festivals and book fairs are in tune with the flickering of
                    the canals' surface, with their curlicue, sirocco-perused scribblings.
                    And of course, turning this place into a capital of scientific research
                    would be a palatable option, especially taking into account the likely
                    advantages of the local phosphorus-rich diet for any mental endeavor.
                    The same bait could be used for moving the EEC headquarters here from
                    Brussels and the European parliament from Strasbourg. And of course, a
                    better solution would be to give this city and some of its environs the
                    status of a national park. Yet I would argue that the idea of turning
                    <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3164603">Venice</placeName> into a museum is as absurd as the urge to revitalize it with new
                    blood. For one thing, what passes for new blood is always in the end
                    plain old urine. And secondly, this city doesn't qualify to be a museum,
                    being itself a work of art, the greatest masterpiece our species
                    produced. You don't revive a painting, let alone a statue. You leave
                    them alone, you guard them against vandals - whose hordes may include
                    yourself.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="44">
                <p>Seasons are metaphors for available continents, and winter is always
                    somewhat antarctic, even here. The city doesn't rely on coal as much as
                    it used to; now it's gas. The magnificent, trumpetlike chimneys
                    resembling medieval turrets in the backdrop of every Madonna and
                    Crucifixion idle and gradually crumble away from the local skyline. As a
                    result you shiver and go to bed with your woolen socks on, because
                    radiators keep their erratic cycles here even in hotels. Only alcohol
                    can absorb the polar lightning shooting through your body as you set
                    your foot on the marble floor, slippers or no slippers, shoes or no
                    shoes. If you work in the evening you burn parthenons of candles - not
                    for ambience or better light, but for their illusory warmth; or else you
                    move to the kitchen, light the gas stove, and shut the door. Everything
                    emanates cold, the walls especially. Windows you don't mind because you
                    know what to expect from them. In fact, they only pass the cold through,
                    whereas walls store it. I remember once spending the month of January in
                    an apartment on the fifth floor of a house near the church of Fava. The
                    place belonged to a descendant of none other than Ugo Foscolo. The owner
                    was a forest engineer or some such thing, and was, naturally, away on
                    business. The apartment wasn't that big: two rooms, sparsely furnished.
                    The ceiling, though, was extraordinarily high and the windows were
                    correspondingly tall. There were six or seven of them, as the apartment
                    was a corner one. In the middle of the second week the heating went off.
                    This time I was not alone, and my comrade-in-arms and I drew lots as to
                    who would have to sleep by the wall. "Why should I always go to the
                    wall?" she'd ask beforehand. "Because I'm a victim?" And her
                    mustard-and-honey eyes would darken with incredulity upon losing. She
                    would bundle up for the night - pink woolen jersey, scarf, stockings,
                    long socks - and, having counted <foreign xml:lang="it">uno, due, tre!</foreign> jump into the bed as
                    though it were a dark river. To her, an Italian, a Roman, with a dash of
                    Greek blood in her veins, it probably was. "The only thing I disagree
                    with in Dante," she used to remark, "is the way he describes Hell. To
                    me, Hell is cold, very cold. I'd keep the circles but make them of ice,
                    with the temperature dropping with every spiral. Hell is the Arctic."
                    She meant it, too. With the scarf around her neck and head she looked
                    like Francesco Querini on that statue in the Giardini, or like the
                    famous bust of Petrarch (who, in turn, to me is the very image of
                    Montale - or, rather, vice versa). There was no telephone in that place;
                    a jumble of tuba-like chimneys loomed in the dark sky. The whole thing
                    felt like the Flight to <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/357994">Egypt</placeName>, with her playing both the woman and the
                    child, and me my namesake and the donkey; after all, it was January.
                    "Between Herod of the past and Pharaoh of the future," I kept telling
                    myself. "Between Herod and Pharaoh, that's where we are." In the end I
                    fell ill. Cold and dampness got me - or rather my chest muscles and
                    nerves, messed up by surgeries. The cardiac cripple in me panicked and
                    she somehow shoved me onto the train for Paris, as we both were unsure
                    of the local hospitals, much though I adore the faccedilade of
                    Giovanni e Paolo. The carriage was warm, my head was splitting from
                    nitro pills, a bunch of <foreign xml:lang="it">bersaglieri</foreign> in the compartment were
                    celebrating their home leave with Chianti and a ghetto blaster. I wasn't
                    sure whether I would make it to Paris; but what was interfering with my
                    fear was the clear sense that, should I manage, in no time at
                    all - well, in a year - I'd be back to the cold place between Herod and
                    Pharaoh. Even then, huddling on the wooden bench of my compartment, I
                    was fully aware of this feeling's absurdity; yet as long as it could
                    help me to see through my fear, absurdity was welcome. The trundling of
                    the carriage and the effect of its constant vibration on one's frame
                    did, I suppose, the rest, rearranging or messing up my muscles, etc.,
                    even further. Or maybe it was just that the heating in the carriage
                    worked. At any rate, I made Paris, had a passable EKG, and boarded my
                    plane for the States. In other words, lived to tell the story, and the
                    story itself to repeat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="45">
                <p>"<placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3175395">Italy</placeName>," Anna Akhmatova used to say, "is a dream that keeps
                returning for the rest of your life." It must be noted, though, that the
                arrival of dreams is irregular and their interpretation is
                yawn-inspiring. Furthermore, should dreams ever be designated a genre,
                their main stylistic device would doubtless be the non sequitur. That at
                least could be a justification for what has transpired thus far in these
                pages. Also, that could explain my attempts over all these years to
                secure that dream's recurrence, manhandling my superego in the process
                no less savagely than my unconscious. To put it bluntly, I kept
                returning myself to the dream, rather than the other way around. Sure
                enough, somewhere along the line I had to pay for this sort of violence,
                either by eroding what constituted my reality or by forcing the dream to
                acquire mortal features, the way the soul does in the course of one's
                lifetime. I guess I paid in both ways; and I didn't mind it either,
                especially the latter, which would take the form of a Cartavenezia
                (exp. date, Jan. 1988) in my wallet, anger in those eyes of a particular
                variety (trained, and as of the same date, on better sights), or
                something equally finite. The reality suffered more, and often I would
                be crossing the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3373405">Atlantic</placeName> on my way home with a distinct feeling of
                traveling from history into anthropology. For all the time, blood, ink,
                money, and the rest that I shed or shelled out here, I never could
                convincingly claim, even to myself, that I'd acquired any local traits,
                that I'd become, in however minuscule a manner, a Venetian. A vague
                smile of recognition on the face of a hotelier or a trattoria proprietor
                didn't count; nor could anyone be deceived by the clothes I'd purchased
                locally. Gradually, I've become a transient in either realm, with the
                failure of convincing the dream of my presence in it being somewhat more
                disheartening. That, of course, was familiar. Yet I suppose a case could
                be made for fidelity when one returns to the place of one's love, year
                after year, in the wrong season, with no guarantee of being loved back.
                For, like every virtue, fidelity is of value only so long as it is
                instinctive or idiosyncratic, rather than rational. Besides, at a
                certain age, and in a certain line of work at that, to be loved back is
                not exactly imperative. Love is a selfless sentiment, a one-way street.
                That's why it is possible to love cities, architecture per se, music,
                dead poets, or, given a particular temperament, a deity. For love is an
                affair between a reflection and its object. This is in the end what
                brings one back to this city - the way the tide brings the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3183462">Adriatic</placeName> and,
                by extension, the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3373405">Atlantic</placeName> and the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2633321">Baltic</placeName>. At any rate, objects don't
                ask questions: as long as the element exists, their reflection is
                guaranteed - in the form of a returning traveler or in the form of a
                dream, for a dream is the fidelity of the shut eye. That's the sort of
                confidence our own kind is lacking, although we are part water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="46">
                <p>Should the world be designated a genre, its main stylistic device
                would no doubt be water. If that doesn't happen, it is either because
                the Almighty, too, doesn't seem to have much in the way of alternatives,
                or because a thought itself possesses a water pattern. So does one's
                handwriting; so do one's emotions; so does blood. Reflection is the
                property of liquid substances, and even on a rainy day one can always
                prove the superiority of one's fidelity to that of glass by positioning
                oneself behind it. This city takes one's breath away in every weather,
                the variety of which, at any rate, is somewhat limited. And if we are
                indeed partly synonymous with water, which is fully synonymous with
                time, then one's sentiment toward this place improves the future,
                contributes to that <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3183462">Adriatic</placeName> 
                or <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3373405">Atlantic</placeName> of time which stores our
                reflections for when we are long gone. Out of them, as out of frayed
                sepia pictures, time will perhaps be able to fashion, in a collage-like
                manner, a version of the future better than it would be without them.
                This way one is a Venetian by definition, because out there, in its
                equivalent of the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3183462">Adriatic</placeName> 
                or <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3373405">Atlantic</placeName> or <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2633321">Baltic</placeName>, time-alias-water
                crochets or weaves our reflections - alias love for this place - into
                unrepeatable patterns, much like the withered old women dressed in black
                all over this littoral's islands, forever absorbed in their eye-wrecking
                lacework. Admittedly, they go blind or mad before they reach the age of
                fifty, but then they get replaced by their daughters and nieces. Among
                fishermen's wives, the Parcae never have to advertise for an opening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="47">
                <p>The one thing the locals never do is ride gondolas. To begin with, a
                    gondola ride is pricey. Only foreign tourists, and well-off ones at
                    that, can afford it. That's what explains the median age of gondola
                    passengers: a septuagenarian can shell out one-tenth of a
                    schoolteacher's salary without wincing. The sight of these decrepit
                    Romeos and their rickety Juliets is invariably sad and embarrassing, not
                    to say ghastly. For the young, i.e., for those for whom this sort of
                    thing would be appropriate, a gondola is as far out of reach as a
                    five-star hotel. Economy, of course, reflects demography; yet that is
                    doubly sad, because beauty, instead of promising the world, gets reduced
                    to being its reward. That, in parenthesis, is what drives the young to
                    nature, whose free, or, more exactly, cheap delights are free - i.e.,
                    devoid - of the meaning and invention present in art or in artifice. A
                    landscape can be thrilling, but a <foreign xml:lang="fr">façade</foreign> by Lombardini tells you
                    what you can do. And one way - the original way - of looking at such
                    <foreign xml:lang="fr">façades</foreign> is from a gondola: this way you can see what the water
                    sees. Of course, nothing could be further from the locals' agendas as
                    they scurry and bustle about on their daily rounds, properly oblivious
                    or even allergic to the surrounding splendor. The closest they come to
                    using a gondola is when they're ferried across the Grand Canal or
                    carrying home some unwieldy purchase - a washing machine, say, or a
                    sofa. But neither a ferryman nor a boat owner would on such occasions
                    break into "<foreign xml:lang="it">O sole mio</foreign>." Perhaps the indifference of a native takes
                    its cue from artifice's own indifference to its own reflection. That
                    could be the locals' final argument against the gondola, except that it
                    could be countered by the offer of a ride at nighttime, to which I once
                    succumbed.</p>
                        <p>The night was cold, moonlit, and quiet. There were five of us in the
                    gondola, including its owner, a local engineer who, together with his
                    girlfriend, did all the paddling. We moseyed and zigzagged like an eel
                    through the silent town hanging over our heads, cavernous and empty,
                    resembling at this late hour a vast, largely rectangular coral reef or a
                    succession of uninhabited grottoes. It was a peculiar sensation: to find
                    yourself moving within what you're used to glancing across - canals; it
                    felt like acquiring an extra dimension. Presently we glided into the
                    <foreign xml:lang="it">laguna</foreign> and headed toward the island of the dead, toward <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3167976">San Michele</placeName>.
                    The moon, pitched extraordinarily high, like some mind-bogglingly sharp
                    ti crossed by a cloud's ledger sign, was barely available to the sheet
                    of water, and the gondola's gliding too was absolutely noiseless. In
                    fact, there was something distinctly erotic in the noiseless and
                    traceless passage of its lithe body upon the water - much like sliding
                    your palm down the smooth skin of your beloved. Erotic, because there
                    were no consequences, because the skin was infinite and almost immobile,
                    because the caress was abstract. With us inside, the gondola was perhaps
                    slightly heavy, and the water momentarily yielded underneath, only to
                    close the gap the very next second. Also, powered by a man and a woman,
                    the gondola wasn't even masculine. In fact, it was an eroticism not of
                    genders but of elements, a perfect match of their equally lacquered
                    surfaces. The sensation was neutral, almost incestuous, as though you
                    were present as a brother caressed his sister, or vice versa. In this
                    manner we circled the island of the dead and headed back to
                    Canareggio... Churches, I always thought, should stay open all night; at
                    least the Madonna dell' Orto should - not so much because of the likely
                    timing of the soul's agony as because of the wonderful Bellini Madonna
                    with Child in it. I wanted to disembark there and steal a glance at the
                    painting, at the inch-wide interval that separates her left palm from
                    the Child's sole. That inch - ah, much less! - is what separates love
                    from eroticism. Or perhaps that's the ultimate in eroticism. But the
                    cathedral was closed and we proceeded through the tunnel of grottoes,
                    through this abandoned, flat, moonlit Piranesian mine with its few
                    sparkles of electric ore, to the heart of the city. Still, now I knew
                    what water feels like being caressed by water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="48">
                <p>We disembarked near the concrete crate of the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/6487167">Bauer Grünwald
                    Hotel</placeName>, rebuilt after the war, toward the end of which it was blown up by
                    the local partisans because it housed the German command. As an eyesore,
                    it keeps good company with the <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/12689490">church of San Moisè</placeName> - the busiest
                    <foreign xml:lang="fr">façade</foreign> in town. Together, they look like Albert Speer having a
                    pizza <foreign xml:lang="it">capricciosa</foreign>. I've never been inside either, but I knew a German
                    gentleman who stayed in this crate-like structure and found it very
                    comfortable. His mother was dying while he was on vacation here and he
                    spoke to her daily over the telephone. When she expired he convinced the
                    management to sell him the telephone's receiver. The management
                    understood, and the receiver was included in the bill. But then he was
                    most likely a Protestant, while <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/12689490">San Moisè</placeName> is a Catholic church,
                    not to mention its being closed at night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="49">
                <p>Equidistant from our respective abodes, this was as good a place to
                    disembark as any. It takes about an hour to cross this city by foot in
                    any direction. Provided, of course, that you know your way, which by the
                    time I stepped out of that gondola I did. We bade each other farewell
                    and dispersed. I walked toward my hotel, tired, not even trying to look
                    around, mumbling to myself some odd, God-knows-from-where-dredged-up
                    lines, like "Pillage this village," or "This city deserves no pity."
                    That sounded like early Auden, but it wasn't. Suddenly I wanted a drink.
                    I swerved into San Marco in the hope that Florian's was still open. It
                    was closing; they were removing the chairs from the arcade and mounting
                    wooden boards on the windows. A short negotiation with the waiter, who
                    had already changed to go home but whom I knew slightly, had the desired
                    result; and with that result in hand I stepped out from under the arcade
                    and scanned the piazza. It was absolutely empty, not a soul. Its four
                    hundred rounded windows were running in their usual maddening order,
                    like idealized waves. This sight always reminded me of the Roman
                    Colosseum, where, in the words of a friend of mine, somebody invented
                    the arch and couldn't stop. "Pillage this village," I was still
                    muttering to myself. "This city deserves..." Fog began to engulf the
                    piazza. It was a quiet invasion, but an invasion nonetheless. I saw its
                    spears and lances moving silently but very fast, from the direction of
                    the <foreign xml:lang="it">laguna</foreign>, like foot soldiers preceding their heavy cavalry.
                    "Silently, and very fast," I said to myself. Any time now you could
                    anticipate their king, King Fog, appearing from around the corner in all
                    his cumulus glory. "Silently, and very fast," I repeated to myself. Now,
                    that was Auden's last line from his "Fall of Rome," and it was this
                    place that was "altogether elsewhere." All of a sudden I felt he was
                    behind me, and I turned as fast as I could. A tall, smooth window of
                    Florian's that was reasonably well lit and not covered with a board
                    gleamed through the patches of fog. I walked toward it and looked
                    inside. Inside, it was 195? On the red plush divans, around a small
                    marbled table with a kremlin of drinks and teapots on it, sat Wystan
                    Auden, with his great love, Chester Kallman, Cecil Day Lewis and his
                    wife, Stephen Spender and his. Wystan was telling some funny story and
                    everybody was laughing. In the middle of the story, a well-built sailor
                    passed by the window; Chester got up and, without so much as a "See you
                    later," went in hot pursuit. "I looked at Wystan," Stephen told me years
                    later. "He kept laughing, but a tear ran down his cheek." At this point,
                    for me, the window had gone dark. King Fog rode into the piazza, reined
                    in his stallion, and started to unfurl his white turban. His buskins
                    were wet, so was his charivari; his cloak was studded with the dim,
                    myopic jewels of burning lamps. He was dressed that way because he
                    hadn't any idea what century it was, let alone which year. But then,
                    being fog, how could he?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="50">
                <p>Let me reiterate: Water equals time and provides beauty with its
                    double. Part water, we serve beauty in the same fashion. By rubbing
                    water, this city improves time's looks, beautifies the future. That's
                    what the role of this city in the universe is. Because the city is
                    static while we are moving. The tear is proof of that. Because we go and
                    beauty stays. Because we are headed for the future, while beauty is the
                    eternal present. The tear is an attempt to remain, to stay behind, to
                    merge with the city. But that's against the rules. The tear is a
                    throwback, a tribute of the future to the past. Or else it is the result
                    of subtracting the greater from the lesser: beauty from man. The same
                    goes for love, because one's love, too, is greater than oneself.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="note">
                <dateline><date when="1989-11">November 1989</date></dateline>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>