<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lagoon</title>
                <author>Joseph Brodsky</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1"><date>May 2025</date></edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Annotations by</resp>
                    <name>Artem Romashov</name>
                    <name>Arina Gracheva</name>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p><!--Описание--></p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p> <!--Источник--> </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p><!--Цель диджитал-проекта--></p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><!--Какие аналитические features были добавлены--></interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <lg type="stanza" n="1">
                <head>I</head>
                <l>Down in the lobby three elderly women, bored,</l>
                <l>take up, with their knitting, the Passion of Our Lord</l>
                <l>as the universe and the tiny realm</l>
                <l>of the pension Academia, side by side,</l>
                <l>with TV blaring, sail into Christmastide,</l>
                <l>a lookout desk clerk at the helm.</l>
            </lg>
        
            <lg type="stanza" n="2">
                <head>II</head>
                <l>And a nameless lodger, a nobody, boards the boat,</l>
                <l>a bottle of grappa concealed in his raincoat</l>
                <l>as he gains his shadowy room, bereaved</l>
                <l>of memory, homeland, son, with only the noise</l>
                <l>of distant forests to grieve for his former joys,</l>
                <l>if anyone grieved.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="3">
                <head>III</head>
                <l>Venetian church bells, teacups, mantel clocks</l>
                <l>chime and confound themselves in this stale box</l>
                <l>of assorted lives. The brazen, coiled</l>
                <l>octopus-chandelier appears to be licking,</l>
                <l>in a triptych mirror, bedsheet and mattress ticking,</l>
                <l>sodden with tears and passion-soiled.</l>
             </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="4">
                <head>IV</head>
                <l>Blown by night winds, an Adriatic tide</l>
                <l>floods the canals, boats rock from side to side,</l>
                <l>moored cradles, and the humble bream,</l>
                <l>not ass and oxen, guards the rented bed</l>
                <l>where the window blind above your sleeping head</l>
                <l>moves to the sea star’s guiding beam.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="5">
                <head>V</head>
                <l>So this is how we cope, putting out the heat</l>
                <l>of grappa with nightstand water, carving the meat</l>
                <l>of flounder instead of Christmas roast,</l>
                <l>so that Thy earliest backboned ancestor</l>
                <l>might feed and nourish us, O Savior,</l>
                <l>this winter night on a damp coast.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="6">
                <head>VI</head>
                <l>A Christmas without snow, tinsel, or tree,</l>
                <l>at the edge of a map- and land-corseted sea;</l>
                <l>having scuttled and sunk its scallop shell,</l>
                <l>concealing its face while flaunting its backside,</l>
                <l>Time rises from the goddess’s frothy tide,</l>
                <l>yet changes nothing but clock hand and bell.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="7">
                <head>VII</head>
                <l>A drowning city, where suddenly the dry</l>
                <l>light of reason dissolves in the moisture of the eye;</l>
                <l>its winged lion, which can read and write,</l>
                <l>southern kin of northern sphinxes of renown,</l>
                <l>won’t drop his book and holler, but calmly drown</l>
                <l>in splinters of mirror, splashing light.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="8">
                <head>VIII</head>
                <l>The gondola knocks against its moorings. Sound</l>
                <l>cancels itself, hearing and words are drowned,</l>
                <l>as is that nation where among</l>
                <l>forests of hands the tyrant of the State</l>
                <l>is voted in, its only candidate,</l>
                <l>and spit goes ice-cold on the tongue.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="9">
                <head>IX</head>
                <l>So let us place the left paw, sheathing its claws,</l>
                <l>in the crook of the arm of the other one, because</l>
                <l>this makes a hammer-and-sickle sign</l>
                <l>with which to salute our era and bestow</l>
                <l>a mute up-yours-even-unto-the-elbow</l>
                <l>upon the nightmares of our time.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="10">
                <head>X</head>
                <l>The raincoated figure is settling into place</l>
                <l>where Sophia, Constance, Prudence, Faith, and Grace</l>
                <l>lack futures, the only tense that is</l>
                <l>is present, where either a goyish or Yiddish kiss</l>
                <l>tastes bitter, like the city, where footsteps fade</l>
                <l>invisibly along the colonnade,</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="11">
                <head>XI</head>
                <l>trackless and blank as a gondola’s passage through</l>
                <l>a water surface, smoothing out of view</l>
                <l>the measured wrinkles of its path,</l>
                <l>unmarked as a broad “So long!” like the wide piazza,</l>
                <l>or as a cramped “I love,” like the narrow alleyways,</l>
                <l>erased and without aftermath.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="12">
                <head>XII</head>
                <l>Moldings and carvings, palaces and flights</l>
                <l>of stairs. Look up: the lion smiles from heights</l>
                <l>of a tower wrapped as in a coat</l>
                <l>of wind, unbudged, determined not to yield,</l>
                <l>like a rank weed at the edge of a plowed field,</l>
                <l>and girdled round by Time’s deep moat.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="13">
                <head>XIII</head>
                <l>Night in St. Mark’s piazza. A face as creased</l>
                <l>as a finger from its fettering ring released,</l>
                <l>biting a nail, its gazing high</l>
                <l>into that nowhere of pure thought, where sight</l>
                <l>is baffled by the bandages of night,</l>
                <l>serene, beyond the naked eye,</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="stanza" n="14">
                <head>XIV</head>
                <l>where, past all boundaries and all predicates,</l>
                <l>black, white, or colorless, vague, volatile states,</l>
                <l>something, some object, comes to mind.</l>
                <l>Perhaps a body. In our dim days and few,</l>
                <l>the speed of light equals a fleeting view,</l>
                <l>even when blackout robs us blind.</l>
            </lg>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="note">
                <date>1973</date>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>